<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ioiefull and blessed reuniting the two mighty &amp; famous kingdomes, England &amp; Scotland into their ancient name of great Brittaine. By John Bristoll</title>
            <author>Thornborough, John, 1551-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1039:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ioiefull and blessed reuniting the two mighty &amp; famous kingdomes, England &amp; Scotland into their ancient name of great Brittaine. By John Bristoll</title>
                  <author>Thornborough, John, 1551-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, &amp; are to be sold in Paules Church yarde at the signe of the Crowne by Simon Waterson [, London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>John Bristol = John Thornborough.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IOIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL AND BLESSED REV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting the two mighty &amp; famous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, England &amp; Scotland into their <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient name of great Brittaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN BRISTOLL.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device with the framed blazon or coat of arms of the University of Oxford. McKerrow 285</figDesc>
               <p>SAPIENTIAE ET FELICITATIS</p>
               <p>ACADEMIA OXONIENSIS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by IOSEPH BARNES, &amp; are <hi>to be ſold in Paules Church yarde at the ſigne of the Crowne by Simon Waterſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie, IAMES by the grace <hi>of God, King of great Brittaine, France, &amp; Ireland defender of the faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ioyfull; and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie proclaimed vnion of your Maieſties two famous kingdomes, England and Scotland into the name of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> in one dutifull obedience of all, to one Royall Rightful Soveraigne over all, is the very Treaſurie of the whole State; where your Maieſtie is ſole, &amp; high Treaſurer of weale publique: &amp; your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne authoritie, beautified with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for executing lawes: with wiſedome for determining Right: with mercy, and grace, for releeving diſtreſſed Subiects, is
<pb facs="tcp:19007:3"/> the glorious abundant Treaſure it ſelfe. And albeit I haue in my two bookes, like the poore widdowe, offered into your Treaſury, but only <hi>two mites,</hi> yet I hope (&amp; for that doe moſt humbly pray your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious favor) that your highneſſe will bee pleaſed in goodnes to accept my humble ſervice; &amp; duty, &amp; to lay vp my two mites with the reſt of the rich Treaſure, though in the account, they be ſcarcely reckoned for a farthing. I haue with that care, and caveat as is meete, only obſerved the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of your highnes proclamation, and with dutiful, and due regard, left all other incident circumſtances, and great conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations to the wiſedome of the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Commiſſioners, authorized by your Maieſtie in both your Parliaments. As for all others, which diſlike mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, and diſtaſte my zeale, eſteeming my labours loſt, and better left vndone, then my reputation left vndone amonge them; I eſteeme them only <hi>tanquam Peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios
<pb facs="tcp:19007:3"/> Cenſores</hi> trampling on truth, and cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their eies in their heeles, and not in their head; nevertheleſſe I deſire (if may be) to avoide their kicking, and ſpurning: if not, yet becauſe I knowe my farthing good ſilver, able to indure touch, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, I haue without other reſpects in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this booke, ſcattered abroad the fire of my zeale, to ſhew it felfe in its own ſhine, and placed my happyneſſe in your Maieſties approving mine endevours, knowing that the king of kings acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the poore widdowe to haue caſt in more into the Teaſury, then al the rich men. Me ſelfe verily doe caſt in all that I haue; and for my part, doe iudge it everie mans part, to depart from all, where hee oweth all. To this I can only adde my dayly praiers, and doe preſently, and will ſtill powre them forth to the God of all glorie, and mercie, lifting vp hands, &amp; heart, that his manifold, and dayly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings may bee multiplyed vpon your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb facs="tcp:19007:4"/> perſon, vpon our gracious Queen, and vpon your Royall Seede for ever: and that all your kingdomes may flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to your owne hearts deſire, for ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of foes, and endleſſe comfort of all your loving Subiectes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties faithfull Subiect and humble ſervant: Io. BRISTOLL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19007:5"/>
            <head>THE IOYFVLL AND HAPPY vnion of the two famous kingdomes Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Scotland into the name of Great Brittaine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE State of England, and Scotland may bee reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the condition of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, and Iuda, not only for emulation, who haue moſt right to the Royall perſon <note place="margin">2. Sam. 19.</note> of the Kings Maieſtie. for their defence, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but alſo for that the two kingdomes were at firſt both but one. Beſides, God, as he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by his Prophet, did alſo at firſt alike leade both them, and vs, <hi>with Gords of a man, euen with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſe. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Bands of loue.</hi> And as it pleaſed God, for ſinne of people to breake thoſe Bands, even both the <hi>Staffe of bands, and of bewtie, to diſſolue the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoode</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> 
               <hi>of Iſraell, and Iuda,</hi> ſo, for the iniquitie of our forefathers, God brake the <hi>Staffe of bands,</hi> ſignifying mutuall loue, and alſo <hi>Staffe of bewtie</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19007:6"/> ſignifying order of government, and brought in vpon them, &amp; vpon their poſterity, even to theſe <note place="margin">Iſ 9.</note> our latter daies, <hi>a ſtaffe of diuiſion, and yoke of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> vpon theirs, and our ſhoulders; which nowe for al that, out of the riches of his mercie, he hath alſo broken in peeces, making al one againe, as he ſpake by his Prophet Ezechiel, concerning Iſrael, <note place="margin">Ezec. 37.</note> and Iuda, ſaying, <hi>I wil make them one people in the land, vpon the mounetaines of Iſraell, and one king ſhall be king to them all, &amp; they ſhall be no more two peoples, neither be diuided, any more henceforth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This foundation laide, as proiect of our whole purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The trueth ſheweth it ſelfe howe two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ſevered in place, not much differing in lawes, nor diſſonant in language, but only diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing heretofore in neighbourhoode, may bee comprehended vnder notion of one name, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing, when one ruleth both, and both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Subiect to one, they are no more two, but one body, lincked in like duety, and knit togither in one bande of obedience. To doubt this is in Strangers, ignorance, but in Subiects, a great offence.</p>
            <p>For who ſo conſidereth that many Shires, with the principality of Wales, heretofore made one England, cannot but confeſſe, that likewiſe Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; Scotland, with al their territories, Ilands,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19007:6"/> Shires, and Countries make now one great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and al the people of both the mighty nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Brittaines: and that the Kings Maieſtie hath done as princely an Act in vniting both the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes into one name, as hee did in vniting the Armes of both the Realmes into one Scutchion hauing a like Right in both. For all great Brittaine being his Maieſties inheritance, all his Subiects within that continent are Brittaines.</p>
            <p>Iuſt, and reaſonable was the demande of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> chiefe Governour of Latines, in vniting Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, and Latines, ſaying, <hi>Ex vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gente vnum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 8. lib.</note> 
               <hi>oportet eſſe populum, vnam fieri rempub: eande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perij ſedem, idem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnibus nomen.</hi> And albeit the Latines were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, for ſake of Weale publique, to preferre Romanes before themſelues, and bee called by their names (as the Hiſtory there far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reporteth) <hi>Quoniam ab alter vtra parte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedi neceſſe eſt (quod vtriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> benè vertat) ſit hat ſanè patria potior, &amp; Romani omnes vocemur:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe the caſe not ſtanding ſo with vs, that Scottiſh ſhould be called by our name, nor we by theirs, me thinks, a thirde name of great Brittaine might eaſily, &amp; equally pleaſe both: otherwiſe as King <hi>Deiotarus</hi> cut of al his children, ſaving one, <note place="margin">Plut. 3. mor</note> becauſe he would leaue the kingdom but to one: ſo ſhould Engliſh, ſwallowing vp name of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, or Scottiſh drowning name of Engliſh, prooue ſuch a Vine, which to bring but one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19007:7"/> grape to ripenes, is content that all Branches bee cut of, but one. But the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here is not, which of the branches ſhould beſt proſper, but how all the branches may flouriſh, which abide in the Vine: and verily the queſtion carieth in it ſelfe, his anſwere. Abide in the Vine. This <hi>Vine is but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 37. 19</note> 
               <hi>one,</hi> though of many branches, and much fruite. And thanks be given to God, that his Maieſty by publique Proclamation, hath divulged the inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and faſt grafting of each branch, and al fruite into his owne Royal perſon, as into a fruitfull and flouriſhing vine, even into the head of the whole body, of howe many ſo ever partes conſiſting. Wherein his Highneſſe hath laid the firſt ſtone, as he is the true and only foundation of happy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: and yet, as yet, like <hi>Apelles</hi> faſhioning onlie the exquiſite and moſt excellent beauty of <hi>Venus</hi> in the head, but I hope alſo &amp; will pray for perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the reſt: that the ſaying may be true. <hi>Rex velit honeſta, nemo non eadem volet:</hi> and that an vniverſal vnion may be as happie in <hi>ſucceſſu,</hi> as it is moſt iuſt by proclamation in <hi>inceptu.</hi> That the head going before, the whole body may followe after in imitation, to worke out perfection of the deſired happy vnion. That it may be verified, <hi>quod diu parturivit tandem peperit;</hi> &amp; what God had in his provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce long purpoſed is fulfilled in theſe our happy daies. And that by no meanes that of the Poet may be imputed to vs, either by diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19007:7"/> to our head, or diſagreeing among our ſelues, <hi>humano capiti vartas inducere formas.</hi> Grammarians doe obſerue, that <hi>Metallum,</hi> is ſo called, <hi>quaſi,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is <hi>poſt,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is <hi>aliud,</hi> becauſe there is ſcarcely found no veine of Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, where is not more of that ſort adioyning to it: ſo among Engliſh and Scottiſh, they are not to bee thought of the true metalline Mine, but as droſſe, &amp; canker, corrupting, &amp; conſuming each other, which ioine not in the vniverſal name of great Brittaine, ſo to continue, and dwel togither, to grow vp and agree togither: ſeeing nature hath made them all of one kinde, forme, complexion, habit, and language growing togither.</p>
            <p>And verily divine is the miſtery of vnion (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the provident wiſdome of nature from God hath ingendred it, or the ſkil of mans reaſon hath obſerved it) where one of, and in it ſelfe, doth out of it ſelfe powre foorth innumerable formes of things; as Brittaine doth, even two kingdomes, &amp; the principalitie of Wales, with many Shires, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Ilands, and people, and yet conteineth them all within it ſelfe: one having many, many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one; where one of many is not divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe, and the many in one make no divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to overthrow the whole; but all are the ſame; whither we reſpect vnion, or diviſion.</p>
            <p>And this doubtleſſe is a divine power, or cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial vertue, not only for our purpoſe, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19007:8"/> &amp; paſſing through the whole world, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king things either ſimple, or coniunct, but one; ſubſiſting, by, &amp; vnder the divine eſſence, which is one; and conſiſting in all his members, &amp; parts vnited, but one; where each, &amp; every part of this vniverſall world, reſpecteth the whole, otherwiſe innumerable, but brought by vnion to a number, without number, even beginning of numbers, which is but one.</p>
            <p>And this is moſt agreeing to the conceipte of wiſeſt Philoſophers, ſkilful in natures Secret: tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, all (whatſoever is) to be but one: and that in the vniverſal nature of things there is an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amitie, and intermixed affinitie,: where all the partes of the whole world accorde, by one tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed continuat ſpirit among them, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact togither with one, and the ſelfe-ſame agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing force, &amp; forceable agreement of nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from one beginning, continued by one meane, and referred to one end; everie particular being knit togither with the whole vniverſality &amp; diverſity of things, &amp; wrapt vp in one round orbe togither, that as partes of this worlde, they may dwell in one Center, or Circle togither.</p>
            <p>To ſhut vp many things in few, and to ſhevve how certainely all things are contained in one, &amp; one doth comprehende all, verily in Schooles of Philoſophers, it is an infallible Maxime, that all things are communicated in one; <hi>Vnum hoc,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19007:8"/> prae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnibus vnum.</hi> This one is al in al. <hi>Ruunt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem omnia, vbi vnitas non firmamentum, difflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, vbi non coagulum.</hi> The demonſtration in our entended purpoſe, is plaine. Many villages make one Shire, many Shires one kingdom, many king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes one Imperial Monarchy: all which is Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and Brittaine al theſe; and the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie poſſeſſing, &amp; governing Brittaine, poſſeſſeth, and governeth al theſe: and the Subiect, knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brittaine, knoweth al, and every of theſe; for al theſe are one, and this one is al theſe. That as this excellent workemanſhip of Vnion ſheweth it ſelfe in the mightie Maſſe, and fabricke of the whole worlde, ſo much more particulerly, and plainely doth it appeare in a modell of the ſame, even in the name, and honour of great Brittaine; where every Subiect ought cleerely to ſee in him ſelfe, that though he be tearmed, the little world, and compact of infinite varietie, and multiplicity of things, yet is he not two, but one man.</p>
            <p>Here let the neere neighbourhoode, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of man, and man, in mutual ſocietie, and participation of profites, which man hath with man (where two friends are but one, and not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>meum,</hi> and <hi>tuum</hi>) confeſſe; that though they are in perſon two, yet in deede doe, with <hi>idem vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, &amp; idem nolle,</hi> enioy the fruition of heaven, with the ſame aſpect, &amp; the commodities of the earth, with the ſame minde; where all things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19007:9"/> to both, and yet proper to each one.</p>
            <p>All which things are alleadged to ſhew that as every kingdome, &amp; State of the world is vphelde with one, and the ſelfe ſame power, &amp; life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the vniverſall world conſiſteth, So now it concerneth al, &amp; every one Subiect, both of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Scotland, to participat in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, tranſfuſed into al, vnder the governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of one: which duety is neglected of him, vvho a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kings deſignement, &amp; right, &amp; againſt his owne incorporation, reiecteth his vniting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the name of Brittaine. And in this vnion, <hi>qui non colligit, diſpergit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where ſacred vnitie is guide, and director, there, even from diſtinct of nature, vſe of mutuall ſocietie, and good of weale publique, many are knit togither inſeperably; and great, and infinite numbers of all Sorts of people, are contained in one narrow compaſſe of neere coniuuction; for ſo the moſt populous and powrefull kingdomes, though two, or mo, vnder one Soveraigne, ſeeme to be, but as one whole body, And the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Weale publique in ſubiection, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but as one man: <hi>ſic enim omnes aquoiure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent omnibus imperature.</hi> And as in al things, ſo ſpecially in this, are we bound, to render al praiſe, and thankſgiving to that thrice ſacred <hi>Vnity,</hi> from whom, as from the firſt author, and fountaine, is ſowen abroad in the world, that fruitful ſeede of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19007:9"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant vnitie; whoſe force draweth many of one houſhold to be of one minde, and is ever doing good, in its owne nature, keeping Iſrael togither, <hi>like a flocke of ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it an hard matter to vnite, and keep them togither, who liue vnder the ſame climate of heaven, &amp; are of like language, manners, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, lawes, cuſtomes, forme of bodie, faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of behavior, yea, and religion: <hi>à religando:</hi> Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the chiefeſt band of hearty vnion. For though the Hand Salamis bee controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <note place="margin">Aelian. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the Athenians, &amp; Megarenſes, yet muſt it be adiudged to the Athenians, becauſe they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved after the ſame faſhion and lawes; as now the ſkilful in the lawes of this land eaſily acknowledge what congruity and affinity is betweene moſt of the ancient lawes of both our kingdomes, more then is to be found betweene thoſe of any other two nations. And albeit the Towne Sidas be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted <note place="margin">Athene 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> betweene the Athenians, &amp; Beotians, yet Epominondas wil adiudge it, to the Beotians and not to the Athenians, becauſe the Athenians called an apple <hi>malum punicum,</hi> but the Beotians called it Sidas. There is betweene Engliſh, and Scottiſh ſmal, or no difference, nay now none at al, in vnion al being Brittaines, not ſo much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Gileadites and Ephraimites in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Shibboleth, or Sibboleth, but al are of one language, &amp; even of one <hi>Canaan language,</hi> only a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19007:10"/> little River Twede is common limit, or rather i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary bounde to both: and al from Twede Southward, is Brittaine within Twede, and al fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Twede Northward, is Brittaine beyonde Twede, yet both on this ſide, &amp; that, al but one Brittaine (<hi>non nos mare ſeperat ingens, exiqua prohibemur aqua</hi>) as al France hath formerly bin divided into two parts, the one beyonde the Alps, the other within the Alps: and all Jndia Weſtward within the River Gange, and Eaſtward beyonde Gange. And all Scithia within Imaus, and without Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. And though the Iland hath bin long time di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into two kingdomes, yet England it ſelfe hath oft times of divers, bin called Brittaine, as by a Surname: and if <hi>pars prototo,</hi> might haue that denomination, much more ought the whole being now made one. Therefore <hi>Linacre, &amp; Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus</hi> of the one part called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Brittaines, and <hi>Iohannes Maior</hi> of the other, affirmed that the kings of England, and Scotland wanted good Councel to adviſe them to marie togither, ſo to make of both one kingdome of Brittaine: &amp; that only envious men, and they who neglected the Weale publiq ue, did hinder this vnion of peace. Which thing King Henry the ſeventh, and King Henrie the eighth, wiſely forſaw, ſeeking by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to vnite both kingdomes into one. <hi>Diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantis ſaepe patriae non aliud eſt remedium, quam ſi ab vno regeretur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19007:10"/>
            <p>Therefore the wiſe men haue moſt religiouſly obſerved two beginnings of things; one of evil, diviſible, imperfect, manifold, called <hi>duallitie,</hi> or <hi>Binarius numerus.</hi> Another of good, indiviſible, perfect, and in name, and nature, alwaies one, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>vnitas.</hi> If <hi>Duallitie,</hi> or <hi>Binarius,</hi> as cauſe effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient beare ſway, then in the aire it breedeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperature; if in citties, families, or kingdomes, wars, and diſcorde; if in the body, diſeaſes; if in the minde of men, vice, and wickednes. But where <hi>vnion</hi> poſſeſſeth chiefe place, her fruites are, to the aire wholſome temper; to citties, families, &amp; kingdomes, mutual loue, and ioie; to the bodie health, and ſtrength; and to the minde, vertue, &amp; godlines. For vnitie admitteth no duallity, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no contrarietie, and by conſequence no infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. But <hi>Duallitie</hi> ſeduced Adam in diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſeeking to know, aſwel evil, as good; who before, was ſole Monarch of the whole earth, and was wholly good, and perfect, both in bodie, and Soule, vntil hee drew with a dubble twiſted corde of contrarieties, vnto his body, in ſteede of health, ſickneſſe, &amp; infirmities; and vnto his ſoule, in ſteede of Righteouſneſſe, ſinne, and miſerie; needing now to ſtrengthen his body, bread; and to repaire his ſoule, grace; euen for body, &amp; ſoule Gods mercy. For ſo he turned the Monarchy of perfect good, into a Monomachie, or duellum of good, and euil, ſin, and righteouſnes peace, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19007:11"/> war, ioie, and ſorrow, ſickneſſe, &amp; health, yea life, and death. And now when the ſole Monarch of the whole earth, left of to abide in the common obedience, and vniuerſal vnion of al things to his creator (albeit al the creatures were before in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary ſubiection, vnited alſo to their ſole Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch <hi>Adam</hi> on earth) yet now everie creature lifteth vp himſelfe againſt his ſole earthly Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and againſt his Succeſſion for euer. The earth wil not yeeld <hi>Adam</hi> bread, but by the ſweat of his browes; the beaſts become wilde, &amp; cruel; yea the earth openeth her mouth againſt the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of diſobedient <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſwalloweth vp <hi>Corah, Dattan, &amp; Abiram;</hi> the waters drowne the whole world, except eight perſons; the poore flie, can, and doth ſometimes choake a man, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving before neither power, nor wil, to doe it; Lice can devoure, and eate vp <hi>Herod;</hi> euen the vileſt, and weakeſt creatures, can, and often doe deſtroy the greateſt Tirants of the earth.</p>
            <p>And in opinion of ſome, the holy Ghoſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in miſterie to open this matter to a man of vnderſtanding, forbearing in the ſecond daies worke, to ſay <hi>all was good;</hi> as is plainely ſaid of al the other fiue daies, <hi>and he ſaw all things good;</hi> not but that the worke of this day, was alſo good, (for al his workes, are, and were exceeding good) but becauſe of <hi>waters,</hi> which in many places of the ſcripture ſignifie troubles, yea intollerable affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19007:11"/> and becauſe of diviſion of waters in that daies worke (<hi>God, being a God, not of diviſion, but of peace</hi>) therfore the holy Ghoſt ſeemeth to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſay in that place, <hi>and it was good.</hi> And yet would not theſe bee miſtaken in their curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as if they concluded the diuiſion of waters in that daies worke, not to be good, (ſeeing that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the clowds diuided from the Seas, are vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden by Gods prouidence, not to powre down and over whelme the earth) for they approue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of conſtructions to be good, as the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the light from darknes, the day from night, and of whatſoeuer into parts, for ornament, and beauty of the forme diuided; but vtterlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne diuiſions of deſtructions, or of diſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which is, <hi>frangere non dividere, comminuere non diſtinguere,</hi> to part the body from the head, or the members from the bodie, to bring order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, vnitie to diſtraction, forme to a Chaos, &amp; <hi>ens</hi> to privation, ſuch diviſion was that, whereof <hi>Caſelius</hi> anſwered the merchant: <hi>Navem ſi divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Macr. 2. ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>nec tu, nec ſocius habebit:</hi> &amp; ſuch diuifion the vnnatural harlot entended, requiring the liuing childe to be cut into two partes, <hi>let it bee neither</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 3.</note> 
               <hi>mine nor thine, but divide it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where two, or three are made one, there is the image of God, of truth, of peace, of fortitude, of praiſe, &amp; of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but where one is drawn, diuided, and torne a ſunder, there breaketh forth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19007:12"/> falſhood, war, feare, diſhonor, &amp; confuſion. They which are of God, embrace the one, and they which are of the deuil, the other. For God both in the Center, and Circumference of truth, is in ſimplicitie, and perfection, one: but the Devil, neither dwelling in this Center, nor ſitting in this Circle, is carried in duallitie, nay contrariety of numbers, oppoſing evil againſt good, whoſe Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being falſhood, the circumference cannot be truth: his is a kingdome divided, and muſt fal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not a Monarchie it cannot ſtand. And yet we reiect not the number of two, ſo they continue, &amp; perſiſt in vnion, as it is written, <hi>they ſhall be two in one fleſh:</hi> but reprobate is that duallitie, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth war in peace, begetting and ingendring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, and contrarietie, controuerſie, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and either of ambition, ſenſleſnes, hatred, quarrel, open diſcorde, or rebellion, doth hinder that ſweete Harmony of vnion; moſt pleaſing to God, and moſt profitable for men, of whom ſaith Tacitus, <hi>In publicum exitioſi, nihil ſpei, niſi per diſcordias habent, tamen libert as, &amp; praecioſa no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina praetexuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But do we not ſee by this vnfolding of things, how the perpetual courſe of trueth, and vnitie, throughout al in the world, doth euen now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and lead me, by the hand, to the matter now in hand? And verily I wil follow thee (<hi>ſacred vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) whither ſoeuer thou leadeſt me, &amp; into, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19007:12"/> ſoeuer Region of vertue, thou intendeſt; I wil not leaue thee, being never vnlike thy ſelfe, alwaies wel accompanied, adorned, and beautified with diverſitie of things, and never alone, and yet ſtil, but one. It is thy doing, that Prudence, the chiefe head, and governour of vertues, the rule and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of al wel doings, and preſcribing to every vertuous action, the manner, order, and courſe, of doing wel, doth ſo knit, and ioine togither al moral vertues, as that by thy ſecret influence they al may be found iointly in al wife Subiectes, and in everie one particulerly with one heart to performe that duety, which both yeeldeth right to the king, and maintaineth peace, and loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men. <hi>Siquidem communis vitae ſocietas, in vnione conſiſtit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing it hath pleaſed his Maieſty by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique proclamation to aſſume the name and ſtile of King of Great Brittaine, <hi>iure haereditario,</hi> it is meete that al loving Subiects not only acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the cleareneſſe of his right, but ioyfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaude and cheerefully follow him herein; leaſt murmuring, they, like evil, and baſe minded ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers follow their Emperor, with an evil wil, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſaying, <hi>malus miles imperatorem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Senec.</note> 
               <hi>ſequitur gemens.</hi> We ſee ſome noble men, yea &amp; the gentlemen in our State daily to purchaſe, &amp; vnite Land, to Land, and Lordſhip, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, &amp; to ſeeke by al meanes to ſhake of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19007:13"/> 
               <hi>in Capite,</hi> and to hold al their Lands in ſome other one more free Tenure. And it cannot bee denied, that to al their ſeveral Courts, al Tenants and free holders willingly performe their ſeveral ſervices: or els are fined by the Lord of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or by his Steward. And may the inferiour Lord expect more homage, from a Tenant, then a King require, both of Lordes, and Tenants, al Subiects to him, and holding al they haue, from, <note place="margin">Tac. 1. Hiſt.</note> by, and vnder him? <hi>pacis intereſt omnem poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad vnum referri.</hi> But al gaine-ſayers &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers, <hi>qui contumaciam potius cum pernicie, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſequium cum ſecuritate malunt,</hi> are not vnlike Meſech, and Kedar, ſpoken of in the Pſalme, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of whom the good King complained to God, and to himſelfe, ſaying: <hi>woe that I dwel with Meſech, and Kedar:</hi> I labour <hi>for peace, and they prepare them to battell,</hi> I ſtuddy vnion, and they <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 2. lib.</note> ſtriue to make diviſion. <hi>Non placeo concordiae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> ſaid that good <hi>Valerius.</hi> But alas, why ſhould <hi>Ephraim beare evill vvillto Iuda, or Iuda vex E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim, fratres'enimſumus:</hi> ſhould not they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both togither vnited nowe into the name of <note place="margin">Eſa. 11.</note> Britaines, as into the name of the beloued Iſrael of God, <hi>flee vpon the ſhoulders of the Philiſtines,</hi> and make ſpoile of their enemies, ſo that the Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Moabites, and Ammonites, euen al their enemies might be ſubdued vnto them: <hi>Duo enim ſunt, quibus omnis reſpub: ſervatur, in hostes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19007:13"/> &amp; <hi>domi concordia.</hi> And verily the vniting the two kingdomes into the name of Brittaine, is not vnlike <hi>that chariot, drawne, with two horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 21.</note> mentioned in Eſay; at ſight whereof, the watch-man cried, <hi>Babilon is fallen, Babilon is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, &amp; all the images of her Gods are ſmitten down to the ground.</hi> For ſo' (except we wil ſmother the childe of <hi>Vnion</hi> in his firſt birth) both Engliſh, &amp; Scottiſh, wil ſoone heare him ſound alow de into the whole world, that al great Brittaine is like Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, which is <hi>as a cittie, at vnitie within it ſelfe;</hi> and Babilon, even diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diſorder, diſcord, and confuſion are confounded, and overthrown; and what King <hi>Egbert</hi> did write in Sand, King <hi>Iames</hi> hath blotted out, and troden vnder foote al the diſhonour thereof, and engraven, as in a marble Srone, the perpetual honor of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by Royal reſtitution. This verily commeth of the <hi>Lord of hoſts, which worketh with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiſedome, and bringeth excellent thinges to paſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> aſked King <hi>Porus</hi> his captiue, how he would be entertained, &amp; <hi>Porus</hi> anſwered, like a King, <hi>Alexander</hi> demaundeth againe: <hi>Porus</hi> anſwereth againe, in <hi>Kingly</hi> manner. <hi>Alexander</hi> aſketh what els, <hi>Porus</hi> anſwereth nothing elſe: for in this, <hi>kingly manner,</hi> euery thing els, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained. And though (God be praiſed for it) the cauſe be not, betweene Engliſh, and Scottiſh in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19007:14"/> aud captivity, as betweene <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Porus</hi> (but two famous kingdomes in right of bloud, vnder one mighty Monarch) yet our great <hi>Alexander</hi> in his high wiſdome conſidering, how theſe two might beſt bee governed, hath in his owne roial heart beſt reſolued it, namely by vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them into one Monarchie, into one govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and into one name; and if any demaunde, how els, verily he muſt be anſwered no way elſe, for in this vnion whatſoeuer elſe is contained. <hi>Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in iſtoc ſunt omnia:</hi> euen, as the Stoiks, (who I thinke neither were in ieſt, nor arrogantly concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) contained vnder Prudence, both iuſtice, and fortitude, and temperance, and whatſoever ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue els, accounting alſo him, who was perfectly wiſe, an Orator, a Poet, a rich man, a very King and an Emperour.</p>
            <p>All bleſſings, and graces, may be thought at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, and companions to vnion, who alone knoweth, how to order al things in government: and is a princely commander of Subiects obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſubduer of gainſaiers, ordering vnrulie affections, bridling vntamed luſtes, reſtraining ſwelling pride, compoſing rebellious appetites, determining al doubts, &amp; rights, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of her iudgement, and yet giving to euerie one, his due, by her diſcretion: And therefore is like the Sunne in the middeſt of heauen, among the Stars; and as the Stars take light of the Sun,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19007:14"/> ſo al bleſſings of Weale publique proceede from this ſacred, &amp; thrice happy vnion into the name of great Brittaine, whoſe glorious light ſhineth to all, and every one hath comfort thereby. It is alſo not vnlike the Soule in the body of man; for in the whole common Weale, it is wholly, and in every part thereof, whither it be of Engliſh, or Scottiſh entire. <hi>Tota in toto, &amp; tota in qualibet parte.</hi> As a ſhining light, it ſheweth a way for common good, and as a reaſonable ſoule, giveth vnderſtanding to the blindeſt body, to ſee the full fruition of al worldly happineſſe: let no man ſhut his eies againſt the Sun, nor refuſe, a living ſoule, for his Carcas.</p>
            <p>If I could expreſſe the image of this vnion in liuely colours, I would ſurely make her a Goddes, faire, and beautiful, having a garland, &amp; crowne of al bleſſings vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her head, &amp; ſitting in a Chaire of State, with al good fortunes, vertues and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces attending her, and as a Goddes in triumphant chariot going into the capitol, or temple of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Iupiter: where alſo the Poets haue found her, but called by another name, even Pallas, who is alſo named <hi>Monas,</hi> that is, vnitie: becauſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Macrob.</note> one only parent, ſhee reſideth in Iupiters braine, even in the chiefe ſeate of his wiſedome; where al the Muſes are her companions, ſo called <hi>Muſae,</hi> quaſi <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is altogither in one; where al the Graces go hand in hand, congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19007:15"/> to vnion their mutual ſocietie; where al vertue, and knowledge, are neere of affinitie, but Iuſtice, and government of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſanguinity to her, her ſelfe ſtil holding primacy over al; as England, &amp; Scotland, are cheerefully looking one towards the other in the name of great Brittaine, &amp; as the two Cherubins did looke one towards the other, in one propitiatory. And thy royal ſtate ô great <note place="margin">Ezech. 28.</note> Brittaine is as <hi>the annointed Cherub.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as in the hart of man is placed fortitude, in his liver temperance, and in his minde Iuſtice, &amp; yet al theſe, with al other vertues are annexed to Prudence, the common ligament of al; ſo is great Brittaine, by vniting al his kingdomes prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, countries, and honours the compleate proportioned forme of al, and al in it both vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally and particulerly, are faſhioned and made fit on every ſide for happy coniunction and mutual correſpondence. For this renowned name of great Brittaine ſtandeth in ſteede of a Loadſtone drawing al into one, chaining them togither with links of loue, as <hi>Liſippus</hi> made an image of fowre mettals mixed togither, gold, ſilver, braſſe, and yron; expreſſing hereby abſolute perfection of vertue, putting in gold, to ſignifie Prudence; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Iuſtice; braſſe, Fortitude; and yron, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: whereof they are altogither ignorant, as if they had never ſeene vertue, ſo much as pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who, to overthrow vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the name of great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19007:15"/> Brittaine, bring no vnion of vertues, euen excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of many Countries, to this ſo excellent worke. But ſkilful <hi>Zeuxes</hi> going about to depaint an abſolute worke of a perfit virgin, tooke not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie view of one womans beautie, but had varietie of many the faireſt, to accompliſh out of al theſe a more excellent, and conſummate forme of bodie.</p>
            <p>Shal we not thinke the kingdome of Fraunce, containing Pickardy, Normandie, the Ile of France, Champaigne, Averne, Dalphenie, Bry, Bloys, Turin, the Dutchie of Aniow, Xantoin, Burgundie, and vniting to it little Brittaine, to be more glorious, in al theſe, being made one, then if but one only of al theſe were that kingdome? Doe we not ſee that the enlarging of the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Spaine, in vniting, and eſtabliſhing diverſe kingdomes, and territories, as thoſe of Aragon, Caſtile, and that of Portugal with others, hath ſo enlarged that kingdome, as that the like hath not befallen other Chriſtian Potentates? Hath not the King of Denmarke, beſide the Cimbrian Cherſoneſe (where Holſatia, Theutomartia, the Dukedome of Sletia, Flenſburgh, Frieſland, and Iuthland doe lie) other ſpacious Ilands, fifteene in number, all comprehended vnder the name Denmarke, and vnited to that Crowne? Did not Iagello, taking to wife in the year, 1380. the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Hedingee the laſt of the blud Royal of Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19007:16"/> after he was inſtalled king there, vnite al his owne principalities of Lithuania, and Samotga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia Provinces of Ruſſia, to the kingdome and <note place="margin">Eſth 1.</note> Crowne of Poland? Did not Ahaſuerus raigne from India to Ethiopia, over an hundred, twenty and ſeaven diuerſe Provinces? And was not he ſo mightie (by reaſon of this varietie, ſubiected, and vnited to his ſole government) that hee was, an hundreth, and fowreſcore daies, ſhewing the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and glorie of his Greatneſſe, to al his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to the mightie men of Perſia, &amp; Media? But to take example of one only Rome for all. How hath it beene renowned through the whole world, by ioyning al the nations of the world into one, euen to it ſelfe? Herehence it was called <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum dea gentium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Roma, communis patria, mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di compendium.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Omnia Romanae cedant miracula terrae,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Propertius</note> Natura hîc poſuit quicquid in orbe fuit.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But the Maieſtie of this Empire grew ſo great by adioining other nations, and bringing them all into one:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Haec eſt, in gremium quae victos ſola recepit,</l>
               <l>Humanum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genus communi nomine fovit</l>
               <l>Matris non dominaeritu, civeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vocavit</l>
               <l>Quos domuit, nexu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pio longinqua revinxit.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And againe,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Feciſti patriam diverſis gentibus vnam,</l>
               <l>Dum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> offers victis proprij conſortia iuris,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19007:16"/>
               <l>Vrbem fecisti quod prius orbis erat.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And ſo may wee ſay of this renowned name of great Brittaine comprehending vs all of diverſe nations in one, vnder our gracious King.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Huius pacificis debemus moribus omnes,</l>
               <l>Quod cuncti gens vna ſumus.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>I could ſet forth, and confirme by ſundry ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, this vniting of many into one, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhew, that the enlarging of dominion conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in vniting altogither into one name, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing diverſe Territories vnder one Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignetie, and government; and that the greater ſtates, and Imperial powers of larger extent and far ſpreading domination are the more durable; <note place="margin">Ariſt. Pol.</note> and that the Monarchie of great Brittaine is like to be hereafter of more durance, ſtrength, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor as partly (comming vnder our Kings govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without conqueſt or conſtraint: <hi>nam errat longè mea quidem ſententia, qui credat imperium ſtabilius aut firmius quod vi adiungitur quam quod facilitate &amp; clementia</hi>) ſo now eſpecially it beeing vnited in the whole, then heretofore divided in parts; his contexture being of a greater frame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before, holding by more then one naile, and vp-holding its own greatnes: even as great buildings endure and ſubſiſt by their owne weight, as the Poet ſpeaketh, <hi>Pondere tuta ſuo eſt.</hi> But I thinke it here, as needeful, to lay open that great fault, imputed to Conſtantine, dividing the Empire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19007:17"/> his Children; whereby of one Empire, hee made three, and withal a memorable diminution of his authoritie, and forces: which part <hi>Brutus</hi> alſo played, dividing this whole Empire of great Brittaine among his three Sonnes: of which, though two parts afterward, namely England, &amp; Wales, were againe in good time vnited: yet Scotland ſtood, till now divided from the reſt, &amp; the reſt from it, till God in ſpecial goodnes, nowe reſtored to former name, and government, al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one againe: for which our King <hi>Iames</hi> may challendge more glory by vniting al into one, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Brutus</hi> or <hi>Conſtantine</hi> dividing it from one: and though <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, was counted the glory of Brittaine as being borne and made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour here: yet may that commendation bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fit our King <hi>Iames</hi> then <hi>Constantine: Tu nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les feciſti Britanias, quod illic ortus factuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>es im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Platan tree hath many goodly Branches, and boughes, and leaues in one body: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Xerxes</hi> in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> crowned him with a golden Garlande: doubtleſſe there is a deſerued glorious garland due to the name of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, bringing forth many goodly boughes, and branches, like to the faire, and wel ſpred Platan tree; or rather for the height of his honor, like the tall, and goodly Cedar, in whom, the dreame of <hi>Nabuchodonoſer</hi> hath beene verified: for he ſaw
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19007:17"/> a tree in the middeſt of the earth, great, &amp; ſtrong, whoſe height reached vnto the heaven, and the ſight therof to the end of the earth: whoſe leaues were faire, and the fruit thereof, much: in which was meate for al, yea the beaſts of the field had <note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> ſhaddow vnder it, the fowles of the aire dwelt in the boughes thereof, and al fleſh fed of it. But <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> heard alſo a watch crying out mightily, hew downe this tree, breake of his bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſhake of his leaues, ſcatter his fruit, that both beaſts, and fowles may be put from him: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe leaue the ſtumpe of his rootes ſtil in the earth. So was the ancient honor, and glory, of great Brittaine: great, and mighty, high to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, faire, and fruitful, &amp; of power over the whole Land from one end to the other: but the higheſt, who hath power over al, did (for the ſin of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants) hew downe this goodly tree; yet left the Stumpe of the rootes in the earth. And out of it the tree is growne vp againe to former beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that we might learne to magnifie the King of heaven, as did <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> reſtored to the honor of his kingdome, to his glory, and beautie againe, to his Counſailours, and Princes, and to the eſtabliſhment of his Throne with augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted glorie.</p>
            <p>And here let vs now conſecrate to al eternitie the ancient name of famous great Brittaine, as a Pantheon of al bleſſings in peace, proſperitie, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19007:18"/> honor: for as Pantheon was a Temple at Rome, rounde, and like to the capacitie of heaven, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were put al the images of their Gods. So, I ſay, in the name and ſtile of great Brittaine, as in a Pantheon, are placed al worldly bleſſings, like ſtars ſhining from heaven, and having their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into the whole body of common weale, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>perfection of beautie in Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Superſtitious antiquity framed falſe Gods, one indued with this vertue, and another with that: this a wiſe, that a warlike, and another a iuſt God: yea for ſo many vertues, they framed ſo manie Goddeſſes, where one Temple might not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to two Goddeſſes, but diſtinct vertues muſt be worſhipped with diſtinct worſhip. So <note place="margin">Val. Max. 1</note> as <hi>Marcellus</hi> dedicating one, and the ſame Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to honor, and vertue, was thought to offende againſt religion. But our happy, and better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed age, reducing al to one, as it teacheth vs in religion both nations to be one, truely to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one true, and only God; ſo in civil things, &amp; government, it offereth only one aboue and for all, that whatſoeuer is ſeperate, and diſtracted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, may be counted, as anathema, excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, divorced, or <hi>as a barren handmaide to be ſold to the vſurer,</hi> vnprofitable, imperfit, or as it were not at all.</p>
            <p>And now, as vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the name of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, is like a Pantheon, and bringeth manifolde
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19007:18"/> abundant bleſſings meeting togither, &amp; concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in one, ſo let vs account our ſelues moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in our ſoveraigne vnitor, in whoſe Royal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and princely Succeſſion, is laide vp al our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and dwelleth al our happynes; even as that worthy <hi>Scipio,</hi> is ſaid therefore to be borne, that there might be one, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al vertue ſhould ſhew it ſelfe effectually, and abſolutely perfect: <hi>hic eſt Scipio, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dij immortales naſci voluerunt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Val. Max. 6 9.</note> 
               <hi>vt eſſet in quo ſe virtus per omnes numeros effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer ostenderet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the voice of trueth it ſelfe; England, and Scotland are ſo naturally vnited in the name of great Brittaine, that the one neerely alyed to the other, can no longer be an alian, or ſtranger, one, to the other, except it may be ſaid, that, <hi>Quia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt, non eſt meus, ipſa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> damno eſt mihi proximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> So this natural coniunction ſhould be no v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, becauſe it is both natural in the Soile, and real in the Subiect. But albeit the Romanes put into the Temple called Pantheon that precious <note place="margin">Macrob. 3.</note> gemme named <hi>Vnio,</hi> divided and cut in two, yet we with al our goods and geare, ought willingly be borne into the boſome of great Brittaine, <hi>quae fundit in omnes imperium,</hi> not diſtributing vnion into parts, but knitting vp al parts into one, as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceroes</hi> orator had al ſciences, and <hi>Aristotles</hi> good man al vertues, as <hi>Cato</hi> was counted like perfect in al vertues, or as the divine <hi>Plato</hi> ſealed vp in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19007:19"/> man, the leſſer world, whatſoever vertue was in the whole world, or rather as <hi>Eden the plentifull</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 28.</note> 
               <hi>garden of God ſealing vp the ſumme of all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and glorie,</hi> was fraight and deckt with <hi>all manner of precious ſtones, the Rubie, the Topaze, and the Diamond, the Chryſolice, the Onix, &amp; the Iaſper, the Saphir, the Emeraude, and the Carbun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and gold.</hi> Even now may it be ſaid of this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal name of Brittaine, as it was ſaide of Rome. <hi>Imperij virtutum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnium lar,</hi> and <hi>virtutum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium latiſſimum templum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ancient time it was counted ominous, if a ſtone fell, or a dogge came among brethren. And <note place="margin">Cic. Off. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> was wont to curſe thoſe, who by ſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, and head-ſtrong opinion attempted to ſet a ſunder thoſe things, which nature coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither. And now if any factious Tribune of the people interpoſe himſelfe to divide vs, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the peace of Iſrael, thinking there is good fiſhing in troubled waters, and that the honours, and benefits, they hunt after, are attained in <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbata Republica:</hi> whereof they vtterly diſpaire in a peaceable State, <hi>quia in concordia ordinum, nullos ſe vſquam eſse vident:</hi> verily ſuch are not vnlike Medea, who ſo diſperſed her brothers limmes, that they could not be gathered againe: <hi>cuius etiam vultu laeditu pietas:</hi> as the Mariners at Sea wel obſerue in the two ſtars Caſtor, and Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux, that if one without the other, appeare, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19007:19"/> foreſee a troubled Sea: but peaceable, and quiet without ſtorme, and without danger in the ſight of both togither.</p>
            <p>The principality of Wales ſhall witneſſe this truth, which never receaved any thing more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial for the people there, then vniting that Country to the crowne &amp; kingdom of England. For whileſt it was alone without his brother, it was ſubiect to ſtorme, ful of contentions, war, &amp; ſhedding of bloud but ioined with his brother, it flouriſhed with peace, and at this day is bleſſed in the vniformity of government there eſtabliſhed. And in mine opinion, it is well obſerved in the Cronicle of Wales, how God was not pleaſed with the firſt change of the name of Brittaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the name of England; for preſently followed the terrible and cruel invaſion of the <hi>Danes,</hi> &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the conqueſt of the <hi>Normans.</hi> But memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is it, that the Brittaines ruled al the whole Ile togither, with the out Iles of <hi>VVight, Mon,</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Angliſee, Manaw</hi> in Engliſh Man, Orkney, and Ewyſt, 1137. yeares before Chriſt, and after the yeare of his incarnation 688. even to the death of <hi>Cadwallader,</hi> the laſt King of Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and of the noble race of Troians. Which when in ſucceeding age many mightie &amp; famous Kings of England, conſidered, they laboured by al meanes to recouer and reſume the name and ſtile of Kings of great Brittaine, accounting it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19007:20"/> to leeſe any iot of the honor of there moſt princely progenitors. And therefore King <hi>Knute,</hi> King of England, mighty in his dominions of Swethen, from Germany to the North poles, with Norway and Denmarke, having obtained proſperous ſucceſſe in warring againſt Scotland, is recorded after his death, the mightieſt prince in the Weſt parts of the world, and of al the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jle of Brittaine. And ſo <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer, for the good ſucceſſe he likewiſe had in Scotland, is recorded king of al Brittaine; &amp; <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſecond, ſurnamed <hi>Curtmantle,</hi> is alſo for like ſucceſſe, recorded king of al Brittaine. And if they be Renowned and honored with name and ſtile of Brittaine, which by rightful deſcent, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, were inheritours but to one part only, though by their fortunes in warre, they alſo clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the other; what rightful title, muſt we then acknowledge, moſt iuſtly now to belong to his moſt excellent Maieſtie, in the imperial crowne of both, who by lineal deſcent inheriteth both. Which thing ſeemeth in his highneſſe late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation to be ſtrongly and truely enforced: for that his Maieſty doth not covet any new affected name, but aſſumeth a title warranted by authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical charter, and records of great antiquity, not borrowed of forraine nations, but from the actes of his progenitours, both before and ſithence the conqueſt, who had not ſo iuſt, nor great cauſe, as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19007:20"/> his Maieſtie hath:</p>
            <q>Cauſa iubet ſuperos melior ſperare ſecundos.</q>
            <p>Here I wiſh I had as many eies, as <hi>Argos,</hi> to looke into their deviſes, who ſeeke to divide Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from Scotland, &amp; Scotland from England, renouncing the name of great Brittaine, leaſt ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one, they might as the forenamed ſtars, appeare togither, ſhine togither, and bring ioy togither. I would then not ſpare to lay open, (as <hi>Cneius Flavius</hi> did reveale to the world the tricks and miſteries of Lawyers of that time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſaid to put out their eies, and to cut their purſes) how alſo theſe Adamants hinder the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural power, and vertue of the load ſtone: whom I cal Adamants, aſwel for repugnant qualities, as that they be truely Adamants, even Sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> practiſing rather in diſobedience, diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ruine of al, to lay hands vpon that is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, then to draw the yron, nay golden chaine of lincks of loue, in obedience to the king, and for common peace, and preſervation of men.</p>
            <p>But herein ſuch imitate the deviſe of <hi>Q Fabius Labeo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Val. 3. 3.</note> ſeeking to haue the ſhip of common weale divided in partes; as when by compact of league with <hi>Antiochus</hi> he ought to receiue halfe part of <hi>Antiochus</hi> ſhippes, cut them al in the middeſt, craftely, ſo to defraude <hi>Antiochus</hi> of his whole Nauy: or elſe imitate they <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herod. 1.</note> dividing great Rivers into many litle Brookes, til they be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19007:21"/> paſſable, but even dried vp: for ſo theſe ſeeke to ſtay the maine &amp; mighty Streame of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by dividing it, and in dividing, to make it of ſundry kindes, vnlike it ſelfe. Such dividing, into parts, is diſioyning of the parts, by diſioyning diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, and by diſmembring, ſpoyling, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">Plin. 36. 17.</note> the ſtone <hi>Scyros,</hi> which whole and firmely compacted, doth ſwim and floate aboue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to ſincke, and be drowned, becauſe it is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But our two famous kingdomes with al their provinces, ſhires, and Countries vnited into the name of great Brittaine, are like the goodly and pleaſant river <hi>Danubius,</hi> which paſſing by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Countries keepeth his name, til it enter into <hi>Illiricum:</hi> where receiving into it ſixtie other ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of diverſe other names, leeſeth not only his owne and al their other names of parts, but is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iſter,</hi> one for al containing al.</p>
            <p>Here I require both of Engliſh, and Scottiſh, is either of them now, as a people diſiointed one from the other? Or as Sande without Lime? Or ſcattered ſtraw without binding? Or as <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes running divers and contrary waies, with fire-brands of diſſention among them? Nay here in the glory of great Brittaine is renowned, that King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his Royal iſſue doe gather togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that, which was ſcattered, and vnite that, which was divided, and reſtore that, which vvas loſt, and ſaue that, which was endangered even
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19007:21"/> by this meanes, vniting al in one name of Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as it was ſaide of Rome, vniting ſo manie Countries into it ſelfe, al parts which diſagreed heretofore are now well agreeing. Heerevpon Rome was ſaid to be <hi>anchora a fluctuanti mundo:</hi> &amp; as he faith in <hi>Tacitus, regnae bellag, per Gallias ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fuêre donec in noſtrum ius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cederetis.</hi> So hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily doeth this vniverſal coniunction of all vnder one head, take away al diſcorde, and maintaine coniunction of loue for everlaſting continuance. Onely they, which wil be alone, and not contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder one name of great Brittaine, are not bound vp with the ſheaues, nor carried home in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Barne, and therefore are like gleanings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter harveſt, left behinde in the field, ſubiect to ſtorme, they come not <hi>two and two</hi> into this <hi>arke,</hi> and whatſoeuer remaineth alone, <hi>extra arcam, perit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such are not vnlike that captaine, whom <hi>Xer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Herod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> rewarded with a garland, for eſcaping aliue, when al other Souldiers were ſlaine, and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he came alone without the reſt, he hanged him: and as the <hi>Athenians</hi> in the warre with the <note place="margin">Herod. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Aeginetae,</hi> when one returned, without his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, ranne al vpon him, and killed him, aſking where were the reſt? And what can ſuch (I pray you) as ſeperate themſelues from the happy vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of al Brittaines anſwere for themſelues, if they be called to account. Can any be Engliſh, &amp; not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19007:22"/> Scottiſh, can any be Scottiſh, and not Engliſh? Let that outcry againſt the Romanes be ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated againſt ſuch, ſaying: <hi>Quintilius Varus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vs our Legions, where are our ſouldiers, what is become of them? Where are the Engliſh where are our Scottiſh, let al reſtore themſelues, &amp; each one the other to the name of Brittaines. And ſo I ſay to al, and everie one of both nations, <hi>Cedo alterum.</hi> (For I feare leaſt this name <hi>Cedo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> be yet ſcarcely fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d among many: but I cal alowde where art thou, <hi>Cedo alterum,</hi> giue vs thy ſelfe, bring in thy friend, yea yet another, and another, be not wanting to the weale publique; <hi>vna navis bonorum omnium,</hi> al good Subiects are conteined in one Shippe of common Weale, <hi>numerum non habet illa ſuum,</hi> one is not perfit without the other: for Brittaines Subiect ought maintaine mutual ſocietie for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good. As for others diſclayming vs, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning themſelues, only I wiſh they may all bee of the ſame conſort, and ſocietie with vs, for, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrix cauſa dijs placuit,</hi> though, <hi>victa Catoni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit many great, and mighty Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates one earth make a great Shew of <hi>copia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum,</hi> by copious recital of many Provinces, &amp; kingdomes; as if his Maieſtie ſhoulde intitle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by al the ſeveral Shires vnder his dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and not by one honorable Title of great Brittaine comprehending al: yet to ſhew how this miſliked
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19007:22"/> ſome, it is recorded when the Emperors Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador comming to the <hi>French</hi> King rehearſed the Emperours ſtile at large, which conſiſted of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dominions and names of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries; the <hi>French</hi> king willed his Herralde to repeate and ſay over the name of <hi>France</hi> as many times as the other had rehearſed the ſeveral titles of his maſters do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: intimating that one name of <hi>France</hi> wel compacted and vnited of many particulers into one general name, was better then diverſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer names of many countries. And when <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 4. Dec. 5. lib.</note> 
               <hi>Flaminius</hi> heard how his army was terrified, at the recital of many his enemies forces, of their diverſitie of names, of countries, of Armor, and of multitudes, <hi>Dahae, Maedi, Caedu ſij, Elemei, Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phracti, &amp;c.</hi> Speare men, Horſe men, Foot men, Archers, &amp;c. Oh ſaith he, what a doe is here, with numbers, and diverſitie of numbers: al theſe are but only Sirians, and make a great ſhew, like that great Supper, which mine hoſt at <hi>Chalcis</hi> dreſſed for me, and for my followers, with much variety, and marveile at the diverſitie of the diſhes, and yet al was but of one fleſh, though of ſo many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers dreſſings. The Riuer <hi>Peneus</hi> may better ſerue <note place="margin">Herod. 7.</note> for inſtance: it divideth it ſelfe, and floweth into many divers Rivers, and everie one of theſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in his diviſion, hath a proper name to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, one after this name, and another after that: but al theſe meeting in one, and becomming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19007:23"/> one great, and mighty River, do, now looſe the particuler names, which they held being divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and are called by one general name, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, namely <hi>Peneus. Non ſunt multiplicanda en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſine neceſſitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not reaſonable that brethren from one pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſhoulde bee divided in one houſe, though they be ſevered in diſtinct place: but be as fingers to one hand, knit togither by common iointes for mutual offices: even as the brethren <hi>Molionides,</hi> are poetically imagined to haue but one body: or rather the three <hi>Gerio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> to haue many bodies, but one ſoule, and one minde; not vnlike to that of <hi>Pithagoras, vt vnum ex pluribus fiat,</hi> many in name, but one in deed. And as when <hi>Piſo</hi> vvas commended to poſteritie for frugalitie, I doubt not, but he was wiſe withall; and as when <hi>Lelius</hi> was renowned for wiſedome, I doubt not, but he was iuſt withal: and <hi>Metellus</hi> for pietie, I doubt not, but he was temperate withal: and <hi>Aristides</hi> for Iuſtice, I doubt not but he was valiant withal: yet I know that the denomination, is ever but of one, though it containe things two, and moe: as the Temple conſecrated to two brethren <hi>Caſtor,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Suet. Iulius.</note> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> was named only <hi>Castors</hi> Temple: and the munificencie of two Conſuls, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> was called only <hi>Caeſars</hi> munificencie: and even many imaginarie ſhewes, and ſhaddowes haue ſeemed compleat, in deciphering one thing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19007:23"/> only: yea the very images of excellent men, haue beene patterns, and reſemblances of many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummat vertues in one: as <hi>Plutarchs Alexander, Xenophons Cirus, Homers Vliſſes, Virgils Aeneas, &amp; Lucians Imagines,</hi> in ſteede of al.</p>
            <p>And as there is a common Idea, and infolded notion of al things in the minde of man, ſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verviewing the whole race and tract of things in the world, doth tel vs, that as many peculiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent properties, may be, and are in one man, &amp; he over them, as ſole Monarch over al the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of worthieſt vertues; ſo a king vnder his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial power hath to him ſubiected many Shires, States, Citties, Honors, Provinces, &amp; kingdomes himſelfe being ſole Soveraigne, and Lord over al. Therefore though magnanimity only, was attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to <hi>Cirus,</hi> only modeſty to <hi>Ageſilans,</hi> onlie wiſedome to <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> ſkil to <hi>Phillip,</hi> &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to <hi>Braſidas:</hi> yet <hi>Alexander,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, was furniſhed, and ful-fraight with all theſe. And <hi>Quintus Metellus</hi> is reported to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <note place="margin">Pet Crin. 13. 5.</note> and poſſeſſe togither, ten of the chiefeſt, &amp; greateſt things, that euer he deſired (as if hee had at once ten Provinces vnder his commaund) and was knowne a mighty warrier, a ſweete oratour, a great commander, to proſper in his greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, to be in greateſt honor, of great wiſedome, a chiefe Senator, plentiful in children, rich of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and moſt renowned in the Citty. So copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19007:24"/> hath one man beene ſtored with plentifull variety of manifold graces, al theſe at once dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in him, and he wel ordering them; euen as one free, and abſolute Monarch may, &amp; doth rule many mighty, and divers Nations, knit in one by obedience, and loue among themſelues, and by law, and luſtice from the king, who by his lawes ſpeaketh alike to al, is heard of al, and vnderſtood of al: <hi>vna, eadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> communi voce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe the name of great Brittaine hath beene long time eclipſed, or rather like thoſe voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">Plut.</note> which Antiphon ſaide were kept cloſe, and frozen vp in the Winter, vntil the heate of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſhining Sunne reſolued the frozen, and faſt bound aire, that they might bee againe diſcloſed. Comfortable is the warmth of this bleſſing, in the Sunſhining day of our ſoveraigne king; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not only clowds are ſcattered, but the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned name of great Brittaine breaketh forth as a gladſome voice from frozened aire, &amp; commeth forth, as a Bridegrome out of his chamber, long time before lockt vp like a priſoner. Doubtleſſe this is our yeare of Iubile, a year of delivering the Captiue, of making the bond, free, and of ioy, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in ſort, and true ſence to vs, <hi>Annus Platoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> wherein things are come about againe to be as they were, (<hi>Iure Poſtliminij</hi>) to recover our ſelues, and be reſtored to name, &amp; fame of great, and glorious Brittaine, long, &amp; lately diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19007:24"/> two kingdomes, but now moſt happily, &amp; ioie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſubiected, &amp; revnited in al the government thereof vnto one only Soveraigne, moſt wiſe, and moſt religious governour of the ſame.</p>
            <q>Deus haec benigna reſtituit in ſedem vice.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Doubtleſſe this is the Lords doing and it is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veilous in our eies,</hi> this is the day the Lord hath made for vs to reioice, and be glad therein. For as it is ſaid, we owe to God our ſelues, for creating vs, when we were not; and more then our ſelues, for re-creating, and reſtoring vs, when wee vvere loſt: So ought al good Subiects thinke the daies more happy, and ioyful, in which they are nowe, as it were new borne, then thoſe, in which they were firſt borne, as is wel ſaid; <hi>non minus illuſtres, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iucundi ſunt illi dies, quibus conſervamur, quàm quibus naſcimur. Happie art thou, ô Iſrael, ô people ſaved by the Lorde, who is like vnto thee?</hi> Thou wert loſt, and art found, bond, and art free, Eclipſed, and art glorious, dead, and art aliue, thy name forgotten, and beholde, it reſoundeth even among hard rocks, and in the hollownes of mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; thy beautie withered, and behold thy val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies ſtand thicke, repleniſhed, and adorned, with faireſt varieties of al good; thy yeares forgotten, thy feathers plucked, and thy ſtrength weakned, and behold thou waxeſt young, and luſtie like the Eagle; yea thine honor, the honor of thine anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent name ruined like an old houſe, but beholde it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19007:25"/> is now repaired, and called after his owne, &amp; olde name; even as <hi>deliaca navis,</hi> torne, and taken in peeces, was renued, and built againe, to his moſt ancient forme, and called ſtil <hi>deliaca navis. Sic rerum ſumma navatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit worldly kingdomes and civil ſtates ſeeme ſubiect to alteration, and do carrie in their outward appearance, faces ſometime ſhining, &amp; glorious as the Sun, and ſometime defaced, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and deformed, conquering, and conquered, triumphing, and enthralled; yet the common weale it ſelfe like the ſhip before mentioned, rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and repaired, is ſtil the ſame; even as the Sunne though eclipſed is ſtil the ſame; and a river ſometime ſhallow, ſometime deepe, ſtil the ſame; and a man now ſicke, now in health, ſtil the ſame. <hi>Reſpublica, enim ſemper vt ciuitas, eſt contigua, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ, perpetuâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſerie compacta,</hi> &amp; though admit it mutation, as our ſtate did long time, ever ſince the firſt diviſion, til this bleſſed day; yet Brittaines co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, was but ſicke for a ſeaſon, til health returned into the whole bodie, by the glory of the head. So as now the firſt and Ancient com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale of great Brittaine is againe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formed to his prime eſtate, ſound, the ſame, &amp; like it ſelfe; and is likely ſo to continue and flouriſh, ſo long as it retaineth the common band of communitie, &amp; individual knot of vnitie. As <hi>Socrates</hi> is ſaide, as long as he is <hi>Socrates,</hi> to bee one and the ſame.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19007:25"/> Whither in childhoode, or manhood, in infancy, or in age, the ſame <hi>Socrates.</hi> But <hi>Heraclitus</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe of the ſodaine change of men and things, that one man could goe into the ſame ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver twice: and ill debtors borrowing mony here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, refuſe payment, becauſe they thinke them ſelues not the ſame men, &amp; plead the day is paſt, and cannot be againe; deluding with that ſaying: <hi>Ego non ſum ego: hodie &amp; heri.</hi> But ſuch concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or rather colluſions are ſimple ruſtical follies; as he ſaith, <hi>ruſticus expectat dum defluat amnis, at ille labitur &amp; labetur in omne volubilis aevum.</hi> For howſoever times alter, yet truth ever ſheweth it ſelfe; as the river <hi>Lycus,</hi> running a long vnder the earth for a long ſpace, breaketh fourth againe, &amp; as is ſaid, <hi>alio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> renaſcitur orbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſleepers in <hi>Sardos,</hi> when they awaked, <note place="margin">Ariſt. Phyſ</note> thought they had paſſed no time: but we ſhal be more drowſie, and ſottiſh then they, if now row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from our long ſleepe, wherein the honourable name of great Brittaine was forgotten, we now not open our eies to acknowledge the happynes of theſe our daies: wherein our hearts may leape for ioy, to ſee our moſt gracious king, as a father of peace, and procreator, protector, and perfitour of Subiects ioie, ſit in Royal ſeate of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines moſt ancient, &amp; moſt abſolute Monarchy: whereby our ſtrength, peace, wealth, and honor is the more increaſed, in that our Soveraigne is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19007:26"/> the more vniverſallie obeyed, and we are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hereby more bleſſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al our fore fathers: of whom we ſay, as <hi>Demaratus</hi> the Corinthian ſaid, that al dead Grecians are deprived of greate ioy, in that they lived not to ſee <hi>Alexander</hi> in <hi>Darius</hi> Chaire. But comfortably ſpake hee in the Comedie: <hi>gaudeo, cum video huius generis reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quias;</hi> and how ioyful is it for vs to acknowledge one an other Brittaines, as it was for them bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Comedie which after ſo long time came to knowledge one of an other: yea now for vs to knowe one an other to bee Brittaines by all ſignes and tokens, <hi>non naevo aliquo aut crepundijs ſed corpore omni.</hi> And though he may bee pittied, which ſitteth alone mourning, and crying: <hi>nec mihi cognatus quiſquam fuit iſto nomine:</hi> yet may both Engliſh, and Scottiſh reioice, becauſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Siſter is a widdow, but all their legitimate children are now of one name, and one bloud, become, and borne againe Brittaines, as it were by a Pithagorical Palingeneſia, even twice Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, as <hi>Hippolitus</hi> was called <hi>Virbius,</hi> becauſe hee lived againe; and was twice the ſame man. <hi>Aeſon miratur; &amp; olim ante quater denos hunc ſe reminiſcitur annos.</hi> And ſurely (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith) <hi>ſparſas &amp; laceras gentilitates colligere &amp; conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctere, eſt, vt it a dicam, rena ſci iubere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſay, and thus we ſing, <hi>Redeunt Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Regna,</hi> even the golden age of Brittaines Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19007:26"/> is come againe: <hi>Alter Tiphis, &amp; altera, quae vehat Argo. delectos Heroas: at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iterum ad Troiam magnus mittetur Achilles:</hi> another gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and chiefe Maſter, of the common weales Ship, and another Arke, or Argoſie, as before, doth tranſport the Nobles, and Commons both of England, and Scotland, to fetch the golden fleece, which <hi>Egbert</hi> that Dragon held ſo long time in his iawes. <hi>Quondam etiam victis redit in proecordia virtus.</hi> Now then, <hi>ſiquid patriae virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> if there be in vs vallour, of men ſtirred vp, with remembrance of the name, and honour of our Country: <hi>Si quid antiquorum hominum:</hi> if any drop of our Anceſtors blood liue in vs: <hi>Si quid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatis:</hi> if any touch of brotherly kindnes, wee ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, but readily imbrace each other, as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Romanes reconciled after long civil war, &amp; ſhedding much bloud <hi>Iungebant Caſtra, &amp; conſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tac. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>abant Cives:</hi> yea and triumph alſo as they did, ſaying, <hi>exurgere, &amp; reviviſcere Romani nominis memoria incipit, &amp; gloria:</hi> vnleſſe it may be ſaide of vs, as of that baſe minded <hi>Vitellius: tant a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedo invaſit animum, vt ſi eum principem fuiſse Caeteri non meminiſsent, ipſe obliviſceretur:</hi> or it may be ſaid to vs Brittaines deſcended from <hi>Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> as ſometimes to another <hi>Brutus,</hi> in an other ſenſe, not here intended: <hi>Dormis Brute, &amp; nones Brutus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Countrie men, &amp; neighbors of Wales, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19007:27"/> Chronicles reporte, deriue them ſelues, from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient true Brittaines: and doe retaine the Brittiſh tongue, though ſomewhat mixed, called <hi>Cambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raec,</hi> which could never be extinguiſhed by anie attempts of <hi>Romanes, Saxons, Danes, Normans:</hi> &amp; that famous Citty <hi>London,</hi> is ſtil by them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Trenwith, of <hi>Brutus</hi> firſt named <hi>Trenovanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And the Countrey it ſelfe is called <hi>Cambria,</hi> of <hi>Camber, Brutus</hi> Sonne, though we cal it <hi>VVales,</hi> a word impoſed by Saxons, naming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>VValſhe,</hi> which is ſtrange; and many mountaines, rivers &amp; cities are among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtil retaining Britiſh names: <hi>extremos pudeat redijſſe:</hi> let vs be aſhamed to bee laſt, or backward, ſeeing another <hi>Arthur</hi> king of all great Brittaine raigneth; leaſt we ſtil ſeeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verawed, and captivated to the Conquerour <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> his wil, and by his beating vs, to bee made, as baſe vaſſals, forgetting our ſelues, our names, and our Countrie, and not daring to challendge, or acknowledge them: even as that baſe Slaue <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> was enforced to yeeld to his Maſter <hi>Mercury,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plau. Amph.</note> and ſay, <hi>pugnis me feciſti tuum, etſi ſum ego, tamen non credomihi, nomen ſimul abstulit cum forma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither doe I eſteeme the change of name, a matter of indifferencie, as if it were all one, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were called Brittaines, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and Scottes. But in my Iudgement it is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to alter all into Brittaines, becauſe it was our moſt ancient, and is the more honorable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19007:27"/> name, except we wil weare the Badge of ſlaverie on our ſleeue, to brag to the world, that we are not aſhamed, to be conquered, ſo to ſhew our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and ſhame, which <hi>Adam</hi> ſought to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, when he once ſaw it. Neither in mine opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is it reaſon, that the now Nobles or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of England, ſhould delight in name impoſed by that Saxon; ſeeing the whole race of Saxons is for the moſt part rooted out by the Danes and Normanes, and none of Saxons blood that vvas Noble, or almoſt but Gentil is left; and ſeeing (as Chronicle reporteth) it was counted in the daies of the Conquerour, a reproach to be called an Engliſh man, or to ioine in mariage with any of the Engliſh (which in my vnderſtanding is Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons nation.) <hi>Redit ad authores genus, &amp; generoſa in ortus exurgunt ſemina ſuos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And verily names, and titles, are matters of great conſideration: vnleſſe, like <hi>Varro,</hi> not caring <note place="margin">Aug. de civ. 1. 22.</note> for name, we ſhould alſo ſay, that the God, whom the Iewes worſhipped, was but the ſame <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and common God of other Countries, though otherwiſe called, <hi>nihil intereſſe cenſens quo nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nuncupetur, dum eadem res intelligatur.</hi> But in the vnion of the <hi>Sabins</hi> and <hi>Romaines,</hi> (as <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> reporteth) this was eſpecially agreed vpon, that the <hi>Sabins</hi> and <hi>Romaines</hi> ſhould aſſume one an others name promiſcuouſly: ſo that by no meanes they ſhould bee diſtinguiſhed by name.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19007:28"/> Andalbeit among vs, cuſtome hath begotten preſcription, yet we may remember, what is wel ſaid in the Commedie: <hi>nunquam it a quiſquam, benè ſubduct a ratione fuit, quin res, at as, vſus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid apportet novi, vt quae prima putes, poſt in experiendo, repudias.</hi> As in the Romane ſtorie, (when it was obiected that innovations, were da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſtate, and nothing was to be done, whereof formerly there was no preſident) ſaith <note place="margin">Livi. 1. Dec. 4. lib</note> 
               <hi>Canuleius. Quid postea? nullane res nova inſtitui debet? &amp; quod nondum eſt factum (multa enim non dum ſunt facta, in novo populo) ea, ne (ſivtilia qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſint) fieri oportet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whileſt we of England were put a part from Scotland, it was reaſon wee ſhould haue a name divided, and diſtinguiſhed from them, &amp; retaine that name, and condition, as pleaſed fortune to impoſe, as <hi>Andromache</hi> ſaith to her Sonne, <hi>ſume, quod caſuſ dedit:</hi> but being reſtored <hi>in integrum,</hi> and every part knit togither, it is a like reaſon we returne to our old name, &amp; ſay, as in the Prophet, <note place="margin">Hoſe 2.</note> 
               <hi>I will goe, and returne to my former huſband, for at that time, it was better for me, then now. And no man, when he hath tasted the new wine, but ſaith the old is better.</hi> So that as the Romaine Empire firſt was a Monarchie, afterwardes governed by two Conſuls, and ſo a long paſſing through divers kindes of governments, til it returned to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate of Monarchie, to be as it was at firſt: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19007:28"/> ſo the ſtate of great Brittaine, firſt was as a Monarchie al governed by one; ſince it was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but nowe it returneth to his Monarchie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Moribus antiquii res ſtat Romana viriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For men wax wearie, in time, of their preſent condition: and Rome <hi>mole laboravit ſua:</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more truely, God ſetteth bounds to al things, which they cannot paſſe: even the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt powers haue their periods. And al worldly kingdomes thus changing, (after long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) ſay, the firſt is beſt; and ſo likewiſe, <hi>vt rerum, it a verborum interit vſus, quem penes est rerum, &amp; vis, &amp; norma loquendi.</hi> But in this caſe neither the thing, nor the name, being changed: but wee lawfully recovering that, which was loſt, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the title of great Brittaine, enioying our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (as we did before) calling al Brittaines, &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding al things in the ſame ſafety, and ſecurity vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der name of greate Brittaine (as before vnder names of England and Scotland) ſay all and each one to other, <hi>paſcite, vt ante, boues, pueri ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite tauros.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a good, and gracious deede to provide for real agreement in al equal coniunction, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual participation. But, in my ſimple opinion, it had beene <hi>verbo tollere, &amp; reipſa relinquere,</hi> only in ſhew to take away difference, but not in deed, without vniting both kingdomes into the name and ſtile of great Brittaine; for, as he complained,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19007:29"/>
               <note place="margin">Cic. Ep. ad Att.</note> 
               <hi>Tirannis occidit? Tirannis vivit?</hi> So if the olde enmity of Engliſh, and Scottiſh be removed, and yet the names ſtil remaine, I feare that the verie names woulde ever put ill men in minde of olde grudge, and incite new variance: as is ſaid of one, that he was <hi>Romani nominis inimicus,</hi> at deadlie hatred with the verie name: where the name is taken for the very cauſe of hatred. As, <hi>eo nomine hostis,</hi> for that cauſe, even for name ſake he is an enemie: even as in Rome, when all things vvere accorded, and all parties pleaſed, only a name, which was in diſlike among them, was thought hinderance to their mutual Concorde, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 2. lib</note> ſaying, <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> placere nomen, id pericule ſum eſſe, id officere, id obſtare libertati:</hi> and therefore the Senate perſwaded, <hi>Lucius, Tarquinius, Collatinus</hi> otherwiſe in al reſpects approved, and beloved of al, even for his names ſake, to forſake his office, ſaying, <hi>abſolve beneficium, amicus abi, exonera ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem vano (for ſan) metu.</hi> This I ſpeake, leaſt retaining former name of Engliſh, and Scottiſh, which heretofore hath beene offenſiue to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we cal (as before is ſpoken) the ill diſpoſed to former oppoſition, as betweene fire, and water, even to <hi>kindle ſuch a fire in Iacob, as wil devour in Iſraell, and no water ſhall bee able to quench it in Bethell.</hi> Where it may be thought more fit, to ſet aſide al difference of former names: <hi>vt exonere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus rempub. vano (for ſan) metu;</hi> as it is ſaid of one
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19007:29"/> 
               <hi>quod nihil eſt metuit, metuit, ſine corpore nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And if any account, the feare of name, nothing, (be it alſo ſay I nothing) yet a man cannot be to care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or feareful of that which is counted even no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſeeing it is ſaid. <hi>Qui cavet, vix etiam cavet, dum cavet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let former deſtructions bee preſent inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Offenſiue diſtinction of names hath bred much wo. In <hi>Italie</hi> faction of Guelphs and Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belines aroſe for name ſake. In Englande much blood for the white and red Roſe. In <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> time feareful diviſion betweene the Veneti and Praſini about colours blew and greene. In which grievous contentions, ariſing firſt of ſmall or no cauſe but only of difference in name and diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of colours, deadly hatred is oft times kindled among former friends, as againſt ſworn enemies. After <hi>Phalarides</hi> death, the <hi>Agrigentini</hi> made a decree that none ſhould vſe <hi>glauca veſte,</hi> becauſe the Tirants did vſe <hi>glaucis ſubligaculis:</hi> for they hated whatſoever, might remember them of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Tiranny. And the Romanes publiquely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that no Romane ſhould be ever called af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the name of <hi>Manlius;</hi> for, becauſe his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 6. lib</note> was diſpleaſing, they would haue his name vtterly periſh. I wiſh that <hi>nomen,</hi> or <hi>mentio ipſa,</hi> the names Engliſh, and Scottiſh, borders, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer feud, warres and bloudſhed betweene the two nations, were not once mentioned within
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19007:30"/> our lips, but as <hi>nomen Pelopidarum</hi> vtterly put out, aboliſhed, and never heard of, as that which is laid vp in ſilence in the Graue: even now that not the leaſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be left, no not in ſport or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ludicra certamina</hi> (as we haue a name of plaie amongſt vs called priſon baſe, one part ſtriving for England, and an other for Scotland, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto vs the variance betwixt both nations) leſt it proue, as that betwixt them two brethren, <hi>Demetrius</hi> and <hi>Perſeus,</hi> king <hi>Phillips</hi> ſonnes; who <hi>in ludicio certamine,</hi> oppoſite one to the other, with their companies divided on both ſides, fell in earneſt vnto a maine deadly warre one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other. I ſay, as neere as may be, theſe oppoſite tearmes of Scottiſh and Engliſh ſhould ceaſe; except they remaine, as only they oughte remaine, Epithits pertaining to one name of great Brittaine, and to one people Brittaines, as al the Iewes of al the ſeveral Tribes, were called <hi>Iacob Gods people, and Iſraell his inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein (ſeeing as <hi>Vegetius</hi> ſaith) <hi>principis eſt pro ſalute Reipublicae, &amp; nova excogitare, &amp; anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua restituere</hi>) both nations ought ioyfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the late proclamation, and in al humblenes of duety, ſubmit themſelues to the kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good pleaſure, ſeeking thereby the common good of Weale publique, and not his owne glory (as they doe, who cal their lands after their owne name, to get a name vpon earth: &amp; as <hi>Valens</hi> the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19007:30"/> Emperor deſired, (according to his ambitious, &amp; vaine-glorious humour,) to call this whole Continent <hi>Valentia,</hi> after his owne name: for which thing alſo <hi>Henoch</hi> the Son of <hi>Caine,</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> a Cittie, was firſt noted,) but as a king moſt gracious, not <hi>natus ſibi ſedpatriae</hi> (as <hi>Hadrian</hi> the Emperour profeſſed before al: <hi>ita ſe rempublica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gesturum, vt ſciret populi rem eſſe non propriam</hi>) thinketh only on the ancient name, <hi>non tam mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, quam aptans,</hi> ſo to roote out remembraunce of former hatred, and to vnite both into one. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor populi non ſuum ipſius, ſed Subditorum quaerit commodum: &amp; officio ſuo ſemper fungitur, vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati conſulens, &amp; ſocietati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chaunge of names hath ever beene thought meete in policie, even where men formerlye Strangers, and of diverſe kingdomes were to bee trained vp togither, and framed in faſhion one to the other: as were giuen to <hi>Daniell, Hananiah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan 1.</note> 
               <hi>Miſhaell,</hi> and <hi>Azariah,</hi> new, and other names. And <hi>Daniell was called Baltaſar, and Hananiah, Shadrah, and Miſhaell Meſach and Azariah A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begnego</hi> of purpoſe, by changing their names, to make theſe forget themſelues, their country, and if it were poſſible, the God of their fathers. And ſo the Turkes haue, from time, to time, in their pollicie changed the olde names of thoſe places, they now poſſeſſe, which before profeſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and when vpon any Conqueſt, they take
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19007:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19007:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19007:32"/> into their government Chriſtians, they impoſe on them new names, to liue like them, and as one people among them: &amp; ſhal we thinke it a wrong or inconvenience, that, if a Grecian Prince or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian king recover againſt the Turke, they afterward aboliſh a name impoſed on them, and calany province, people or city after their old and ancient name? <hi>Et ſi hoc in arido, quid in viridi?</hi> If this be done (<hi>ex facto</hi>) by the children of this world, vnto an evil end: may not his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his princely wiſedome <hi>(fas eſtet ab hoste doceri) (exiure)</hi> for the vndoubted good of the children of light cal to remembrance, and put in <note place="margin">Dio. 52.</note> execution the wiſe councel of <hi>Maecenas</hi> to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus:</hi> to take away al differences, whatſoever, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the meaneſt thinges, which might bee thought on, whither of name or apparell, or anie thing elſe, to the intent all thinges might bee throughly compoſed in one vniforme faſhion, &amp; conformitie among al his Subiects, to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted good?</p>
            <p>It hath beene often obſerved, that <hi>parva ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla neglecta magnum ſaepe excitavit incendium.</hi> And ſores ſleightly cured, break forth into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter danger. And, if I might boldly write my mind without miſtake, I would vndertake ſufficiently to proue, that if the name had not beene chaunged into great Brittaine, it might be feared we ſhould not long (as we ought ever) continue one; &amp; that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19007:32"/> (loue being not without diſſimulation) we would among our ſelues, as is vpbraided to the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of another nation (now not to be here na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) <hi>Ridendo fidem frangere,</hi> and ſo loue, as that we would hate againe. For as a chiefe inhabitant, and commander in <hi>privernum,</hi> being aſked in the Senate at Rome, what peace they ſhould expect, <note place="margin">Livi. 1. Dee. 8. lib</note> auſwered, <hi>ſibonam dederitis, fidam, &amp; perpetuam: ſimalam, haud diuturnam.</hi> So here may it be ſaide, if vnion in name, bring alſo in deed, a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and faithful coniunction <hi>bona fide,</hi> it will doubtleſſe by Gods goodnes, laſt ever: but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I feare (which God forbid) may againe rent in ſunder, and make the <hi>newe breach worſe then the former.</hi> And therefore wiſe was that ſaying; <hi>eiuſdem iuris eſſe debent qui ſub eodem rege victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Curt. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſunt,</hi> and that practiſe of <hi>Romulus</hi> renowned, who by vnion of divers nations, <hi>eodem nomine et</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 1. lib</note> 
               <hi>eodem iure latinos vocavit.</hi> And hereof grew the <hi>Italicum bellum,</hi> becauſe the Latines vnited in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpects, were not ioined <hi>eodem iure</hi> with the Romanes. To ſpeake plaine, wee al confeſſe our vnion in our obedience to the King, as to the head: but yet without that vnion alſo in the name of great Brittaine already concluded, &amp; of other things thereto requiſite (to be farther by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Commiſſioners conſidered.) I feare wee ſhal proue, as imperfect, if not deformed bodie, as <hi>Apelles</hi> (before noted) painted <hi>Venus</hi> only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19007:33"/> in the head, and left al the partes of the bodie vnperfect. Neither can I, for my part, imagine that parte of the bodie well vnited to his heade, which doeth not concurre withal the body in all his parts perfect with the head. <hi>Vt nec pes nec ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put vni reddatur formae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein let natures workmanſhip in our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bodies lead vs to the imitation of her wiſdom, in the government of bodies civil: and as ſhee hath in naturall mixtion reduced the fowre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Elementes into a temperate and agreeing conformitie, by taking away ſuſpition of emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, making them looſe their proper names, and iointly called <hi>miſtionis forma:</hi> ſo ſhoulde wee by temperate diſcretion bee willingly vnited with our neighbour friends into one corporation: eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſeeing the reality of everie thing wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy is to continue in al reſpects the ſame, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a formality of appellation a little changed. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam ducem dum ſequimur non aberrabimus,</hi> ſaid he: and the God of nature hath ſpoken it, ſo that we muſt beleeue, <hi>that a kingdome divided cannot ſtand,</hi> howſoever it may glorie in the multitude of his parts: wherein a common weale may fitly be reſembled to muſical inſtruments; which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever conſiſting of the multitude of ſtrings, yet the harmony is in the vnity of proportion with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable conſent of diſtinct ſounds. Now as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle iarre in muſicke, a little intention or remiſſion
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19007:33"/> of any one ſtring diſcordeth al the harmony: ſo in this excellent muſical concorde of a wel-orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red kingdome, never ſo ſmal difference, though it be but titular betweene the ſeverall partes of one common weale, ſometimes breedeth hatred, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes envy, but alwaies emulation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Phillip Comines</hi> wel obſerved, <hi>finitimorum amulationem nativam eſse:</hi> that it was eſſentiall for neighbour regions to emulate one the other: which is only remedied by taking away the frets and by incorporation making them not now our neighbours, but al one with our ſelues. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſteth the nature of true mixtion (whereat al common weales ſhoulde tende) when every thing remaineth that was, yet nothing as it was; when many contrary things yeelde vp their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety and plurality vnto one, conſiſting of all; which participating of al their reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled natures, impoſeth only a new name, to their new manner of being, which is to be one inſteede of many; &amp; that not by coacervation or appoſition of things without farther mixtion, remaining ſtil diſtinct within themſelues, but by <hi>vnion</hi> of conſociation, which taketh nothing away. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things that were before diſtinct, but their diſtinction. Out of vvhich miſtion wil ariſe excellent temperature, which we hope long to ſee in our Britiſh; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, wherein no humor either of Engliſh or Scottiſh, may be predominant, but <hi>tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19007:34"/> aequabile,</hi> and that <hi>ad pondus</hi> too. Which as it is ſeldome founde any where, ſo it is alvvaies found where it is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with perennity. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch miſtion was that ſaide of <hi>Romulus &amp; Traianus,</hi> and now may it bee ſaide of our King <hi>Iames; diverſas gentes it a commercio miſcuit vt quod genitum eſſet vſquam id apud omnes natu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe viderctur.</hi> And of ſuch mixtion may that of <hi>Zeno</hi> be ſaid, <hi>alterius chorus maior, meus autem concin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior:</hi> an other Kings Empire may be greater, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of diverſity of nations, but ours more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and vnited in one. And this mixtion of both our nations ſo mixed in one, bringeth forth but one titel of GREAT BRITTAINE. <hi>Vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſedleonem,</hi> as the proverbe hath.</p>
            <p>Which I the rather vrge here, againſt <hi>Polite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (if any ſuch be) of this age, who ſeeke to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh faction and oppoſition in the State, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Weale, and thinke nothing better; <hi>quam ſi in commune non conſulant;</hi> who ever haue a <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for an <hi>Oliver;</hi> where feareful experience doth often ſhew the fruites of that Axiom; <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria contrarijs curantur.</hi> Which manner of keeping Subiects one oppoſite, and offenſiue to the other, is a flinty, and fierie ſocietie, even <hi>ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas lapidum, fornicationi ſimilima, quae caſura, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi invicem obstarent, hoc enim ip ſo continetur.</hi> And this practiſe, whereſoever prevailing, is more then Machivelian, even divelliſh ſowing ſeede of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19007:34"/> diſſention in parts, to deſtroy the whole. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it being an infallible, but wofull grounde of truth: <hi>nulla ſalus bello:</hi> It is meete that all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Subiect of great Brittaine, vnderſtand, and profeſſe the other part of that verſe, <hi>pacem te poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus omnes.</hi> For ſo I thinke this Axiome in a State, is better for preſervation of Weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique: <hi>ſimilima ſimilimis nutriuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if I were worthy, here would I adviſe all the Magiſtrates of great Brittaine, which either now doe, or hereafter ſhal beare rule vnder their high Soveraigne, in any partes of his dominions, to remember in al their high honours, that <hi>Cleo,</hi> and <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> tooke contrarie courſes, &amp; were both miſliked in time of their Magiſtracie. For <hi>Cleo</hi> called al his friendes, and old acquaintaunce togither, and renounced them openly, giving the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnderſtand, that now he was ſo advanced, they ſhoulde expect nothing from him for former friendſhips ſake. And <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> anſwered one, wiſhing him to be alike to al, and not partial, that he would not ſit in Seate of honour, and not doe more good to former friends, then to others. But trueth is, in a common wealth, nor diſdaine of former friends becommeth <hi>Cleo,</hi> nor partiall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours <hi>Themistocles;</hi> for communitie regardeth neither any man, neither any cauſe for private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, but is as the Sunne, yeelding alike commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Pli. paneg.</note> comfort to al: which thing I wiſh al, as one man,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19007:35"/> wiſely to perceiue, and willingly performe. And <note place="margin">Zenop.</note> yet may <hi>Cirus</hi> haue in remembraunce, the verie meaneſt of them, with whom ſomtimes he lived. and <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> looking into the Chronicles may remember thoſe, which haue ſaved the king, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any, who ſought to lay violent hands vpon him. And the <hi>Macedonians</hi> may not either grudge, or diſdaine that <hi>Alexander</hi> prefer the <hi>Perſians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them of his owne Country. <hi>Ecquis eſt qui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 6. lib.</note> 
               <hi>neceſſaria ſuffragia pro voluntarijs, &amp; ſerva pro liberis faciat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne into the kings high way for the name of Brittaine: ſeeing his Maieſtie may ſaie, <hi>non me Troia capit,</hi> Scotland alone doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my greatneſſe: and therefore ſpeaketh alſo to England: <hi>ſalve fatis mihi debita tellus:</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is alſo the lot of mine inheritaunce: and both England, and Scotland, wil I make one Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and renew their names into firſt title of great Brittaine, as it were <hi>Ilium in Italiam portans:</hi> (though in removing all the Gods out of Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to giue place to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> only that petty God <hi>Terminus</hi> refuſed, and would not moue) yet let the <hi>Termini,</hi> and bounds of both our nations, &amp; all the people therein contained, willingly giue place to the iuſt pleaſure of their ſole Monarch, and even in this alſo, acknowledge King <hi>Iames</hi> their ſupreame head, and governour: where obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in each Subiect, is like reconciled <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19007:35"/> vtriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regni:</hi> which though before was as angrie <hi>Iuno,</hi> much adverſe to the Romanes, yet now like <hi>Iuno,</hi> out of her very image ſeemeth to ſpeake alowd, <hi>Romam ſe velle ire:</hi> Anger is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, diſpleaſure forgotten, and diſcorde come to a perpetual ende.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Nec quenqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incuſo, potuit quae plurima virtus</l>
               <l>Eſse, fuit: toto certatum est corpore regni:</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And now the whole common weale, <hi>odijs ſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, quieſcit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither may contention, either of antiquity, or any other dignity (whereabout <hi>Albanes,</hi> and <note place="margin">Dionyſ Ha licar. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Romaines,</hi> ſo much contended, and woulde not yeeld one to the other) break this common band of loue among our ſelues, or loyaltie to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who imbraceth both nations with equall and indifferent loue. But we ought to conſider, that both Engliſh and Scottiſh (<hi>quis maior? aeque</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plau. Menec</note> 
               <hi>ambo pares</hi>) making no queſtion of difference for common good ſake, without difference may challendge like intereſt in his Maieſties favor (&amp; <hi>vitula tu dignus &amp; hic</hi>) to be divided equally, and graciouſly among al, by Geometrical proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his Maieſtie ſhal bee pleaſed to deeme meete. Which thing may moue al to mutual kindnes, &amp; reciprocate loue one towards the other, with an orderly conformity of both to liue togither in all peace, and Chriſtian charitie, affectioned to loue one <hi>another, with brotherly loue, and in giving ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19007:36"/> 
               <hi> goe one before the other;</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Lelius; actuo ſavitaeiter aequali graedu exeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur:</hi> not grudgingly, nor contentiouſly, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for prerogatiue of bleſſing; and <hi>birthright,</hi> in his Maieſties favour; as if it might be ſaide to <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> his highneſſe, <hi>haſt thou but one bleſsing my father?</hi> for his Maieſties aboundance, and overſtowing meaſure of honour powreth fourth, as out of a fountaine, ſtreames to fill vp every empty chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, <hi>nemo ex hoc numero mihi non donatus abibit;</hi> and where every one may bee contented: <hi>cuncta aderunt; animus, ſite non deficit aequus.</hi> Herein let vs take example fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Romane</hi> common weale (and ſurely for our inſtruction may it be ſaid, <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vnquam reſp. nec maior, nec ſanctior, nec bonis exemplis ditior fuit</hi>) where <hi>Dyoniſius Halicarnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 5.</note> giueth vs a ſtraunge ſhewe of two Conſuls <hi>Largius</hi> and <hi>Claelius,</hi> who both ſtroue to giue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence one to the other, preferring each other before himſelfe, and reckning one an others worth before his owne: &amp; this done, two or three ſeveral times, neither preſuming to goe before the other, but ſtil refuſing, &amp; could by no meanes either bee perſwaded to take the preheminence one before the other. But is any mans eie evill, becauſe the Kings eie in ſpeciall and gracious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect is good? Doubtleſſe when a king doth not all things <hi>ad voluntatem, ſed ad vtilitatem omnium:</hi> they which miſlike (and yet ſeeme of the ſame
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19007:36"/> league, and ſociety with others) doe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding like <hi>Nahaz</hi> the <hi>Ammonite,</hi> ioine in commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.</note> covenaunt, with others, but on condition only, that they may <hi>thruſt out the others right eies. Hoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec: 6. lib</note> 
               <hi>eſt in commune honores vocare? quaenam ista ſociet as? quaenam cenſortio eſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whoſoever entendeth truely the common good, let him remember, that <hi>Solon</hi> ſaid: the only way to keepe Subiects in vnitie, is to mainetaine an equalitie for al: for <hi>motus,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, is in <hi>inequalitate;</hi> but <hi>ſtatus,</hi> and <hi>quies in aequalitate:</hi> which thing is ſpoken, not to breed, or maintaine parity in condition of men, for that equality were true inequalitie, nay iniquitie, ſo to confound the world. But theſe things are alleaged to ſhew that our gracious Soveraigne may herein (I ſpeak vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der favor) be reſembled to <hi>IANVS,</hi> who had two faces, to looke forward, to looke backeward: for ſo his Maieſtie is ſet in the middeſt, ſole Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of al great Brittaine, to looke on England, to looke backe to Scotland, and with princely &amp; favourable aſpect to countenance both, <hi>Tros Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuluſve fuat, nullo diſcrimine habebo:</hi> where both being made one common Country, that ſaying may wel befit our common Emperor. <hi>Hoſtem qui feriet, mihi erit Carthaginenſis, quiſquis erit.</hi> And there is that equalitie, before mentioned, diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from his Grace and Maieſtie in honouring, and defending both alike<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (<hi>Iuſta pari premitur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tib, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19007:37"/> 
               <hi>veluti cum pondere libra, prona nec hac plus parte ſedet nec ſurgit ab illa.</hi>) where none ought ſtriue contentiouſly, leaſt they ſeeme to offer violence to the kings Grace, or to his honor, or to both: as the Mid wife charged <hi>Pharez</hi> in making the breach between him, and his brother, by forcing his birth before his brothers, through ſtrife in his mothers wombe: whoſe name therfore, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pharez,</hi> which ſignifieth diviſion.</p>
            <p>But our brotherhood is not in ſtrife, as that of <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abell, Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob, Iſmael &amp; Iſaac,</hi> nor as that of <hi>Geta</hi> and <hi>Antoninus,</hi> Sonnes to the Emperor <hi>Severus:</hi> after whoſe death, their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Herodia. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iulia</hi> was forced to divide the Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her ſonnes, ſevering and ſetting them a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into ſeperate governments with a ſea betwixt them, becauſe of their hot contentions and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatred. And God forbid, that we ſhould by oppoſite contentions one againſt another, provoke the common parent of both our nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as thoſe two brethren did their parent <hi>Iulia,</hi> to cry out againſt vs, as ſhee did againſt them: O my ſonnes, you haue found the way, how to bee ſevered and divided by ſea and land, into diſtinct regiments, and as you ſay, the water diuides you one from the other: but how will you divide mee your mother? How ſhal I bee divided betweene you both? Will you diſtract me into parts alſo? As them two louers (mentioned by <hi>Plutarke</hi>)
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19007:37"/> ſtriving for their loue, <hi>dum vter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ſe certatim rapere conatur,</hi> rent her in pieces? Let our ſtrife rather be like that of <hi>Ephestien</hi> and <hi>Craterus,</hi> who <note place="margin">Diodor. 17</note> contended whither ſhould loue their king <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> moſt; in ſo much that <hi>Alexander</hi> was enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to decide the controverſie, adiudging that <hi>Epheſtion</hi> loved the king beſt, and <hi>Craterus Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> beſt. So it pleaſed the king in his ſentence equally to divide his loue, and ſo did they both e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ſtrine to loue: and after this manner did the <hi>Iones</hi> and <hi>Chij</hi> contende in loue to <hi>Hercules:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pauſ. 7.</note> and <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>David.</hi> And ſo I doubte not but our contention is of the like loue, &amp; dutie towards our Soveraigne: but as for hatred and malice amongſt our ſelues, ſo ſeperating vs that we cannot be mixed togither, <hi>Dij talia Graijs, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hostibus illum.</hi> Seeing (as he ſaid) no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Tacit. de Germ.</note> hurt can be wiſhed to our enemies then to be diſvnited among themſelues, and if they will not be at one with vs, that they may bee at oddes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues: <hi>mane at quaeſo duret<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſi non amor noſtri at certe odium ſui. Quando nihiliam praeſtare fortuna maius poteſt, quam ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stium diſcordiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And nowe farther to enforce this vnion into both nations, the rather, becauſe we are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vnder one head and governour: hath not his Maieſtie two eies, to reſpect both kingdoms; two eares, to heare a like the cauſe of both: two ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19007:38"/> to beare alike the burden, and care of both; two hands, to diſtribute honours alike to both; &amp; two feete, to goe, one before the other, yet both alike to ſupport but one body? The inequalitie only is, if we are not alike duetifull, and thankeful; neither doe we, as the Apoſtle<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> exhorteth, <hi>carrie like mindes one towardes another;</hi> nor make our ſelues in our owne conceipts, equal to them of the lower ſorte. And where <hi>Xenophon</hi> calleth Magiſtrates, and mighty men, the kings eies, the kings ears, the kings ſhoulders, yea alſo his hands, and his feete, it is not thereby meant, that they ſhould thinke, they alſo had two eies, to envie one the other; two eares, to liſten after advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or offenſes, one againſt the other; two ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to ſhoue at, and ſhoulder out one the other; two feete, to outrunne, and preuent one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to hands, two catch, &amp; ſnatch, one from the other, or to carrie fire in one hand, and water in the other, or to builde with the one, and to pull downe with the other, or with the one to offer a guift, and with the other a ſtab; <hi>altera manu pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, altera lapidem;</hi> but that their eies, eares, ſhoulders, feete, and hands, are, or ſhould be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall helpers one to the other, for the common good, and publique ſervice of the whole State. And I perſwade my ſelfe, that all Magiſtrates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Maieſtie, of the one, or other nation, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted now in one common name of Brittaines will
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19007:38"/> for publique Adminiſtration of the common Weale, ſo ſee with their eies, heare with their eares, beare vp the head with their ſhoulders, and walke vprightly, <hi>having pure, and cleane handes,</hi> that as the fingers in the hande are diſtinctly divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and yet doe clap, and claſpe themſelues togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for more ſtrength; ſo all of commande and in authority within great Brittaine, though they haue diſtinct offices, yet will ſo concurre, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree togither, that though there appeare among <note place="margin">Aug. de Chatizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disrudibus.</note> them, and their diſtinct publique ſervices, as, <hi>in digitis, diviſio,</hi> it ſhall not bee, <hi>ab vnitate prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And verily the two kingdomes, are like tvvo handes warming and enfolding each other, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing two, yet in one bodie: vvhere if the right hand challendge more neceſſarie vſe, and ſervice in the bodie, then the left, or the left hande, more then the right, &amp; one not readyly yeeld to ioine with the other, as is meete, the head may in his good pleaſure, make choice and vſe of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as in the <hi>Romane</hi> Storie, when <hi>Tribunes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. lib</note> diſagreed for chiefeſt honour, <hi>Quintus Servilius, Conſul,</hi> of much leſſe dignitie, and authoritie, then a king, tooke the matter into his own hands, ſaying, <hi>patria maieſt as altercationem iſtam diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Prudence among Subiectes hath neede intermeddle with all other vertues, and ſhew the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19007:39"/> power of vnion in her ſelfe; where Iuſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth righte, fortitude tollerateth, what ought be borne, temperance reformeth wil, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth anger, moderateth paſſion, and repreſſeth ambition; and al in vnitie of obedience coupled togither, bring forth plentiful fruit, for ſocietie, honour, and ioy. Which thing wel pleaſed <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Furius Camillus,</hi> Dictator of Rome, ſeeing all the Senate, and Subiects of Rome, not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde in the common execution of each office for common good of al, but willingly, and loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both higheſt, and meaneſt to embrace one the other, ſaying, that the common Weale, was flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 6. lib</note> and moſt happie: <hi>ſitales viros in magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratu habeat tam concordibus iunctos animis, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imperare iuxtaparates, laudem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes potius in medium, quam excommuni ad ſe trahentes:</hi> whereof the <hi>Senate, Conſuls,</hi> and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes</hi> gaue teſtimonie, and good proofe, vvhen they all ſubmitted, all authorie to <hi>Camillus,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in themſelues, <hi>nec quicquam de maiest ate ſua detractum, quod maie ſtatieius viri conceſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Brittaines vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, England may not exalt it ſelfe aboue Scotland, nor Scotland ſtriue againſt Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but both as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of one body vnder one head, ought to haue the ſame care one for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it, and if one be honoured, all the members reioice with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19007:39"/> and as in the church, ſo in the common Weale, <hi>one is my doue,</hi> one is my darling, ſhee is the onely beloved of her mother, &amp; deere to her, that bare her; ſo I know there are diverſities of guifts, and differences of adminiſtrations, and diverſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of operations in both; and God hath ſet the members of the whole body, everie one of them, ſeveral in the body, as it hath pleaſed him, but, <hi>omnia ab vno ad vnum:</hi> All from one head, and to one ende. He that is wiſe will conſider this. <hi>Qui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu. eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> 
               <hi>vero curioſiores ſunt, quam capaciores, quaedam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis contentioſè obiectanda, quàm prudenter conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deranda eſſe arbitrantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And nowe ſeeing I haue waded ſo farre in the vnion of Brittaines; Engliſh may not miſlike, that Scottiſh beare office among, and with them, as if they were of a farre Countrey, hunting after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Treaſures, ſerving the king of Babilon, and not as the ſame Subiects to <hi>Hezechias;</hi> for they are of, and for England, as we, and wee of, and for Scotland, as they, and both for both, being made one. Nay rather we ought deſire their ſociety, &amp; reioice in this community, ſetting before our eies for example, that ſaying of <hi>Austin</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints, made fellow heires with Chriſt through the mercie of our good God: <hi>Deus, cum haberet vnicum, noluit eſſe vnum, ſed habere fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</hi> And, (if in humane matters, humane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples more mooue) remembring that <hi>Scipio</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19007:40"/> was as glad of his Brothers preferment as of his owne; and that <hi>Caſtor,</hi> would not be a God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his brother <hi>Pollux,</hi> but would be only <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus,</hi> that his brother might partake with him; as <note place="margin">Aug. de bo. no viduit.</note> is wel ſaid: <hi>habent oculi in corpore magnum hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, ſedminorem haberent ſi ſoli eſsent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tac. 11. An.</note> In the time of <hi>Claudeus,</hi> the Emperor, when it was conſulted that the <hi>Senate</hi> ſhould be ſupplyed with more Senatours, the Peires and Nobles of <hi>France,</hi> long before enfranchiſed free deniſons of Rome, ſought alſo to participate in honours, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracies, and dignities with <hi>Romanes:</hi> and the matter beeing handled on both ſides with greate conſideration, the <hi>Romanes</hi> alleadged againſt the <hi>French,</hi> that <hi>Italie</hi> wanted no ſufficient men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelfe, for it ſelfe. And that there was no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to incorporate others with them, who had beene at ſo deadly hatred, and bloudy warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. What? not private men, not the common people, not ſtrangers, but enemies ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the Senate? Was it not counted for a wonder that the <hi>Athenians</hi> did take only <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charſis</hi> into their Citty? Would the <hi>Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> admit it the <hi>Tyrrheni</hi> to participate in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, though they had done them ſervice? And had their mothers alſo <hi>Athenian</hi> women? But the good Emperour replying, ſaid to the Senatours, that he would aſſume into the Senate, of all his Subiectes, ſuch as he found moſt worthy, of what
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19007:40"/> Country ſoever, alleadging, that his own Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors were deſcended from the <hi>Sabini,</hi> and made of Nobilitie and Senate of Rome, and that the <hi>Iulij</hi> were taken from <hi>Alba, Coruncani</hi> from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merium,</hi> the <hi>Porcij</hi> from <hi>Tuſculum, Etruria,</hi> and <note place="margin">Cic. pro Balbo.</note> 
               <hi>Lucania,</hi> and from al partes of <hi>Italie</hi> choſen into the Senate. And that by this meanes <hi>Italie</hi> was extended, and greatly enlarged, ſo as not only, the people, but al their poſſeſſions, had their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon the ſtate of Rome, and grew into one nation and people of Rome. And that a ſetled ſtate chiefly flouriſhed, when the people in habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting even beyonde the river <hi>Padus</hi> were receiued into the communitie of <hi>Romane</hi> Cittizens. And laſtly, that nothing was more hurtful to the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians &amp; Athenians,</hi> then their refuſal to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the common weale by acceſſe of new and other people. What? Shal not they be admitted becauſe they and <hi>Romanes</hi> haue had deadly feud one againſt the other? So the <hi>Aequi,</hi> ſo the <hi>Volſci.</hi> And yet are nowe al one and the ſame people of Rome. This forcible ſpeach pierced their harts, and prevailed ſo, as that al ſubmitted their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Emperors wiſdome. Which thing I thought good here to remember, not forgetting alſo what <hi>Anna</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dido.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuvrbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoror hanc cernes? quae ſurgere regna, Connubio tali, Troum Comitantibus armis? Punica ſe quantis attollet gloria rebus?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19007:41"/>
            <p>Which if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, as we ſhould, we cannot then but ingenuouſly acknowledge, that good &amp; praiſe worthy was the ſpeech of <hi>Paedaretus,</hi> vvho vnderſtanding hee was not choſen into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Trecenti,</hi> who chiefly bare rule, ſaid, he did glorie there were ſo many, his betters in the common Weale. And no leſſe commendable was his ſaying, who wiſhed, he could raiſe from the dead many moe, ſuch excellent Cittizens; as <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> wel advertiſed, <hi>Titus Octacilius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 3. Dec. 4. lib.</note> 
               <hi>nec tu id indignari poſſis aliquem in civitate Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana, meliorem haberiquamte.</hi> Doubtleſſe the common weale is more happy, and doeth there more flouriſh, where is more choice of worthy honourable men, to be imploied in publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, as neede, and occaſion require. And as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in the hand of the ſtrong man, ſo are the ſucceſſion, and children of ſuch: bleſſed is King <hi>Iames</hi> that hath manie kingdomes, like many qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ful of them: but as for the arrowes, which of them ſhal abide in the quiver, and which of them ſhal be taken forth, and ſent, or ſhot abroad, that is in the power of the Archer: neither may one ſay, why haſt thou taken me; nor the other, why am I left with the reſt: <hi>an non in caelo ipſo ſualuce</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no viduitat</note> 
               <hi>ſol Lunam ſuperat, non vituperat? Et ſtella à ſtella differt in gloria non diſſidet in ſuperbia?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit there be a kinde of iealouſie, and natural ſtrangneſſe among men, vntil they better
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19007:41"/> grow in knowledge one of the other, and do eate, (as our Engliſh Prover be hath) a Buſhel of Salte togither: yet haue wee long ſince ſhaken of that infamie, which <hi>Horace</hi> laid vniuſtly vpon vs, that Brittaines were vncurteous, and vnhoſpitall to ſtrangers: and haue learned to graunt Incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and immunities even to ſtrangers in deed, and to enfranches ſtrange nations for trade with vs, making them partakers of our Rights: much more then ſhould we be leſſe nice of al immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and naturall communitie with vs towardes thoſe, who now are one with vs; that though in the Comedie, cauſe of ſtrangneſſe amonge men be alleadged, <hi>quianec ille te novit, nec tu illum:</hi> yet we ſhould be aſhamed, <hi>quaſi Canes, latratu ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere quem non agno ſcimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea rather ſhould wee reioice to heare by this vnion, how that <hi>Lacedemonij Medizant,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plut Arta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lacedemonizant,</hi> both Scot and Engliſh, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly converſe togither, and are growne into one anothers natures and manners, that like <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilij fratres,</hi> they are all one. And ſhoulde wee wiſh by reaſon of the neighbourhood, and nere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of both nations, as alſo for likeneſſe of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage we ſhould be alone: even as the hiſtorian diſcourſeth of the <hi>Phryges</hi> and <hi>Troiani,</hi> &amp; likewiſe <note place="margin">Dionyſ. 1.</note> other nations, how they were taken for the ſame, &amp; called by one anothers names promiſcuouſly, becauſe they were ſo neere one to the other; and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19007:42"/> the ſame alſo were counted but one nation, and of one kinde, by reaſon they were of the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: a moſt ſure argument (ſaith he) that they be but one people, who agree in one language; as it is moſt abſurde, the inhabitants of the ſame places ſhould differ in language, if they be of the ſame kinde. Why then (as he ſaith) <hi>iube hanc</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ter. Adel.</note> 
               <hi>maceriam dirui, quantum potest, huc tranſfer, vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fac domum.</hi> And according to that reſolution.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>—foederis aequas</l>
               <l>Iungamus leges, ſocio ſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in regna vocemus.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Eſpecially ſeeing they may challendge with <note place="margin">Livi. 1. Dec. 4. lib.</note> vs: <hi>cives eſſe, &amp; licet non eaſdem opes habere, ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem tamen patriam incolere: quare connubium pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus, &amp; ſocietatem, quod finitimis, externiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſolet: nihil novi ferimus, ſedid, quod populieſt, petimus: Vt quibus velit populus Romanus honores mandet.</hi> Was not <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> though no Romane, fetcht from <hi>Sabins,</hi> and made king of Rome? Was not alſo <hi>Lucius Tarquinius,</hi> not ſo much as of Romane blood, made king there? And was not <hi>Servius Tullius,</hi> though borne baſely, &amp; <note place="margin">Liv. ibid.</note> of a bond woman alſo made king there? <hi>Et dum nullum fastiditur genus, in quo eniteret virtus, Romanum crevit imperium.</hi> but no ſuch excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scottiſh blood, his Maieſtie being rightlie, and anciently deſcended of royal Engliſh blood, and his nobles hence forth in their poſteritie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with vs, &amp; we with them, al of Brittiſh blood:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19007:42"/> 
               <hi>an eſſe vlla maior, out in ſignior contumelia poteſt, quam partem civitatis, velut contaminatam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignam connubio haberi? Quid est aliud, quam exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium intra eadem moenia, quam relegationem pati? ne propinquitatibus, ne affinitatibus immiſcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ne ſocietur ſanguis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What may wee ſay more, but render all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble praiſe, and thankes to our good, and gracious God, who by his ſervant our Soveraigne, hath reduced, and reſtored the whole Iland of greate Brittaine, anſwerable to his firſt beginning, and auncient former being; like to one Cittie, even one Ieruſalem, which <hi>is a Cittie, at vnitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelfe. Hoc verè Regium, duos populos vnum efficere.</hi> As the king of kings hath in mercy done to Iew and Gentile, to Grecian, and Barbarian, <hi>fecit vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vnum:</hi> he brake downe the partition Wall, and hath gathered the people, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes togither to ſerue him, <hi>diſſociata locis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordi pace ligavit.</hi> And why ſhould not many, and moe then two kingdomes, as well civilie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in vnitie of Subiection, as many Chriſtian nations continue in vnitie of faith? But that the one hath the ſpirit of God, which is authour of peace, and louer of concorde, directing them: and the other the ſpirit of Satan, authour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and cauſe of confuſion, perverting them, Which thing King <hi>David</hi> well perceaved pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God for his Sonne Solomon, that hee might
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19007:43"/> enioye the fuil poſſeſſion of the whole dominion <hi>from ſea, to ſea,</hi> promiſed to <hi>Iſrael</hi> vnder <hi>Moſes,</hi> but not fully obteined till then, becauſe of the peoples ſins. And albeit for our manifold, &amp; great ſins, this whole Iland hath been overlong divided into two, and forced by former diviſion to many battels, &amp; much ſhedding of blood; yet we praiſe God, that in theſe our daies, the ful poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is reſtored, &amp; giuen to our peaceable <hi>Solomon;</hi> ſo as not only al his own ſubiects even from Sea, to Sea, of both the kingdomes, are in him vnited into one; but even the potent, &amp; powerful neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour kings ſeeke peace, and make league with <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi> even <hi>the kings of Tharſis, &amp; of the Iſles, bring preſents, the kings of Sheba, &amp; Seba brings guifts,</hi> as in the daies of <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This change (even the happieſt chaunge that ever was) from a people ſo divided from one, by Gods eternal decree, and ſpecial mercy, to bee made one, biddeth vs open our eies, &amp; calleth vs a lowd, come, &amp; ſee; <hi>ſpe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, fide<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inquit, maiora vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debis.</hi> For our Iland, formerly for ſin divided (as the <hi>Echinades Inſulae,</hi> were fained by Poets, once far ſeperate, &amp; diſtracted, for contempt of their Gods) is now become like that Iland <hi>Delos,</hi> which though it floated, &amp; was toſſed ſometimes vpon the waters, <hi>àgente in gente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as one waue forceth another; was nevertheleſſe reported to bee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, truly firme, and ſtable. Doubtles that God
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19007:43"/> which hath written in the waters, &amp; the Sea, legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for every eie to ſee, &amp; read <hi>Mare Britannicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> &amp; who hath continually carried in directing the pens, &amp; pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſils of al Coſmographers, Mapmakers, or whatſoever Hiſtoriographers) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Alphon ſus Siciliae</hi> calleth <hi>optimos Conſiliarios mortuos</hi>) not to alter the firſt, &amp; old name, but to cal it in all their writings, &amp; deſcriptions, <hi>Mare Britannicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> hath graciouſly, &amp; miraculouſly effected for the lande alſo, that out of the dead aſhes of olde great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſhould be raiſed eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſelfe ſame Brittain, as the <hi>Phenix</hi> living, and dying, <hi>eſt cadem, ſednon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lactan.</note> 
               <hi>eadem, quia ipſa nec ipſa eſt.</hi> O admirable Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis, &amp; happy change: England, &amp; Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue left, though not loſt, their names, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſerved in the Boſome of great Brittaine: <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duo ſunt, nec forma duplex,</hi> but, <hi>neutru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> videtur:</hi> and of both vs Engliſh &amp; Scottiſh being now Brittaines may it be ſaid, as of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two brethren, <hi>altervter &amp; vter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>; altervter est vter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> autem neuter.</hi> Which I againe call that faire <hi>Phenix,</hi> dying, &amp; living, <hi>eadem, &amp; non eadem, quia ipſa nec ipſa eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which excellent, &amp; wonderful work, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; better to bring to paſſe the good purpoſe of vniting the two kingdoms &amp; people into one, it hath ſeemed beſt to the godly wiſedome of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine prouidence, firſt, &amp; long ſince to knit all our harts in one holy religion, &amp; in the ſame ſervice,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19007:44"/> &amp; godly worſhip, to make vs al like Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God, renewed in Chriſt, and reconciled into one body, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging but one God, &amp; profeſſing but one faith, &amp; religion, the hope of our vocation. Whereby we learne, &amp; cannot but confeſſe, (if, as <hi>Ciprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>conſilioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gubernaculum, lex ſit divina</hi>) that, that common Weale beſt pleaſeth God, which commeth neereſt to the Church of God, that wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Politeans, are beſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that beſt govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments haue correſpondence with Gods lawes; &amp; that thoſe kingdomes are beſt ruled, &amp; the more bleſſed, which are of one heart &amp; one obedience, even as al are one in Chriſt, who is the head, &amp; al vnder his government, are by one ſpirite, but one bodie.</p>
            <p>Wherfore the good Emperors <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Valentinianus</hi> writing to <hi>Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> were bold to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende their government, according to the platform, before deſcribed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>A pietate quae in deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, Reipublicae noſtrae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio pendet, &amp; multa vtrin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> est cognatio, &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciet as, &amp;c.</hi> Which moſt excellent patterne, and forme of government, is after the example of Chriſt, vniting al into one: &amp; this the Pſalmiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth to that <hi>precious ointment, powredon the head of Aaron, &amp; running down his beard, even to the ſkirts of his cloathing:</hi> for ſo doth ſweete, and precious vnion reſt chiefly in the heade, which is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19007:44"/> but one, &amp; from thence run al along, &amp; alike to al the parts of the people, which are but one.</p>
            <p>But ſhame on Schiſme, whither it be civil, or eccleſiaſtical; for it renteth the ſeamleſſe Coat of Chriſt, both in the Church and in the Civil ſtate, even in the doctrine, &amp; ceremonies of the one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth of God; &amp; in chriſtian charitie, &amp; common civillity of the other againſt the peace of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore whoſoever oppoſeth himſelfe againſt the one, or other, is more vnreaſonable, &amp; may be thought more cruell, then the ſouldiers, which would not divide Chriſts ſeamleſſe Coat, but caſtlots, whoſe it ſhould be, ſaying: <hi>ſortiamur cuius ſit.</hi> For it caunot be denied, but that they; which divide great Brittaine, to haue it divided within and againſt it ſelfe, divide that, for which they cannot ſay, <hi>ſortiamur;</hi> ſeeing <hi>cuius</hi> is known, &amp; <hi>ſit</hi> cannot be denied: but <hi>ſortiamur, &amp; cuius, &amp; ſit,</hi> muſt wholly, and only be left to king <hi>Iames,</hi> &amp; to his royal ſucceſſion for ever.</p>
            <p>Only let our contention be, as was that of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> who ſhould be forwardeſt in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging our king vnto the ſeate of his kingdome, ſo nowe to preſerue the poſſeſſion of his kingdome, <hi>ſartum &amp; tectum,</hi> inſeperably vnited to the king, &amp; iointly vnited and vndivided within it ſelfe. <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus rex, vna lex; vnus pater, vna communis patria; vnum caput, vnum corpus.</hi> Let not privat reſpects hinder a common good: let every man be as one
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19007:45"/> man, of one hart &amp; one ſoule, vnited to the kings deſigne, for the everlaſting good of every one. If the king <hi>had commanded thee a great thing, woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest not thou haue done it? How much more then, when he ſaith,</hi> be you all of one minde to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably togither, in one vniforme gouernment, for your owne vndoubted good. <hi>Cedat ius propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um regi, patriae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> remittat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude <hi>in nomine, &amp; omine Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae:</hi> to conſummat this ſtructure of vnion, and to conſecrate it to all eternity, as the <hi>Romanes</hi> did their Temple of concord. Behold, now is the time <note place="margin">Liv. 8.</note> of vniting both nations togither; (as he ſaide) <hi>Si quando vnquam conſociandi imperij tempus epta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, en hoc tempus adeſt, &amp; virtute veſtra, &amp; deûm benignitate vobis datum.</hi> Heretofore, as <hi>C. Marius</hi> ſaid he could not <hi>audire ius prae strepitu armorum;</hi> ſo by reaſon of civil diſcord betwixt both nations the name of vnity was but <hi>as a pleaſant ſong,</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the eare, but not entring into the heart or ſerious conſideration of either part. And ſo vntill this day this contagio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath crept in every where. The name of Brittaine ſeemed as a brutiſh name, al commixtion betwixt vs ſeemed confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, any mutation for vnion ſake an vtter ſubuerſion of all the ſtate. But now the matter is come <hi>extra Rubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conem: iacta eſt alea:</hi> the matter is proceeded in: <hi>aut nunquam tentes aut perfice.</hi> Such a matter of ſtate is not ſlightly to be intended. And I know
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19007:45"/> that al the honorable Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners on both ſides thinke every one of them ſelues not to be imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this ſo great buſines, only as <hi>pro Conſule</hi> and in his own perſon, but <hi>pro Conſulibus, &amp; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune omnium;</hi> &amp; therfore will bee aſſembled like wiſe <hi>Romanes,</hi> who after long diſſention, and part takings, made ful reconcilement &amp; concord per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall for all matters in <hi>Aede Concordiae.</hi> And I doubt not, but al Subiects wil in all places, as the <hi>Graecians</hi> did after long variaunce embrace that ioyful <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> agreed on, for good of al, not for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion ſake, as among heathen, but for conſcience ſake, as among ſuch, which truely know, and feare God, who is author of Vnity, &amp; but one God: that ſo there be henceforth, a perfit, and perpetuall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, according <hi>to the lawes of Medes, &amp; Perſians, which may not, nor cannot be altered;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, <hi>inimicitias mortales, amicitias im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortales eſſe debere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Only yet I would ſet before all mens eies that worthy ſpeech of the renowned <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi> king of <hi>Romanes,</hi> in the reconcilement of Rome, and Alba, &amp; repreſented vnto vs in vniting Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; Scotland by our gracious king. <hi>Quod bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Liv. 1. Dec. 1. lib</note> 
               <hi>fauſtum felix<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit populo Romano, ac mihi vobiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Albani, populum omnem Albanum, Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> traducere in animo eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Civitatem dare plebi: primores in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres legere: vnam vrbem: vnam Rempublicam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: &amp;, vt exvno quondam in duos populos diviſa
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19007:46"/> Albanares eſt, ſic nanc in vnum redeat.</hi> And now alſo concerning the name I recite only a poetical fable, yet moralized no fable: that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Neptune. &amp; Pallas</hi> did ſtriue, whether of them ſhould giue name to <hi>Athens,</hi> it was agreed, that hee, or ſhee ſhould name the Citty, who could bring the beſt guift for common good. Wherefore <hi>Neptune</hi> did ſtrike the Shore, &amp; it brought forth an horſe, fore ſhewing that <hi>Athens</hi> ſhould be warlike: but <hi>Pallas</hi> gaue the Cittie an Oliue, ſignifying peace, &amp; that the Citty ſhould flouriſh by peace: where vpon, peace being more profitable, then warre, <hi>Neptune</hi> was enforced to yeelde his intereſt; and <hi>Pallas</hi> gaue the name. Oh how bleſſed are the peace makers? Howe beautiful are their feete? How glorious, and ioyfull the light of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance?</p>
            <lg>
               <l>—pax optima rerum,</l>
               <l>Quas homini noviſſe datu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt pax vna triumphis</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Innumeris potior.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>King <hi>Iames</hi> doue-like brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the Oliue branch, ſheweth that the vvaters are abated, anger a ppeaſed, dangers eſcaped, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows fled, and that ſalvation, and ioy entereth the Arke of great Brittaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>God ſaue the King.</hi>
               <signed>JOHN BRISTOLL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19007:46"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
